<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The French King proved a bastard: or The amours of Anne (Queen to Lewis XIII.) With the Chevalier de Roan.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 114 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40460</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2185B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99827097</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99827097</idno>
            <idno type="VID">31510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40460)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 31510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1886:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The French King proved a bastard: or The amours of Anne (Queen to Lewis XIII.) With the Chevalier de Roan.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition. Published by authority.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[8], 5-52 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Abel Roper at the Mitre in Fleet-street near Temple-Bar,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Price 4 d.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis, --  XIII, --  King of France, 1601-1643 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE FRENCH KING PROVED <hi>A Baſtard:</hi> OR THE AMOURS OF ANNE (Queen to <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII.) With the Chevalier <hi>de Roan. The Second Edition. Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Abel Roper</hi> at the <hi>Mitre</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet</hi> near <hi>Temple-Bar,</hi> 1691. Price <hi>4d.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>John</hi> Lord <hi>Lovelace,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis ſmall Treatiſe, like a Travel in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Mountains of the Moon, for the Bed of <hi>Nile,</hi> being a full Inquiry into the <hi>Little Birth</hi> of our <hi>GREAT LEWIS,</hi> Your Lordſhips Favour to the Subject of this Hiſtory, has encouraged the fixing ſo No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a Name before it: Nor let Our Mighty Monſieur's Idolizers themſelves take Offence at the Theme, it being, perhaps, not the leaſt of his Honour, that ſo Diminutive a Seed ſhould give Root and Production to ſo Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious a Spreading Greatneſs: Nor can I do his Homagers, and Adorers a kinder piece of Juſtice, than making a Conſecrated Relique of his very Swaddling-Clouts. I confeſs, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, I have taken the eaſier Work in hand; the Delineation of his minuter Original, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſomething a fezible Undertaking, when the Deſcription of his fuller Growth, the Manhood of our Prodigious Hero, is almoſt Impoſſible: Impoſſible, indeed, when all the publick Declarations, the whole Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing World around him, have ſo juſtly, and ſo unanimouſly confeſs'd their Inability of matching his Lineaments, even amongſt <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> and <hi>Turks;</hi> and truly if the leaſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling Feature of him can be found in the ſpacious Creation, we muſt look amongſt the Remoter <hi>Indies</hi> for it; and conſider Our
<pb facs="tcp:31510:4"/> Great <hi>Lewis</hi>'s Ambition, as only a more Hideous, Wild, Indian <hi>Delirium, running a Muck at all Mankind.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But while I preſume to commit this piece into your Lordſhips Protection, my Duty leads me to a juſt and awful Veneration of that Honour to which I Addreſs. In all the Rapidity of our late Driving <hi>Jehu's,</hi> your Lordſhip carries this Triumph, that in their higheſt Exaltation, and moſt formidable Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valence, you never bent a Knee. Your Spirit was too Maſculine to flow with a Tide, and choſe rather ſingly to ſtand the Indignation of Power, than herd amongſt the Flatterers of it. And if ſo much true Britiſh Merit, as ſhines in your Lordſhip, ſo late a Royal Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourite, makes ſo new a Figure in Court, we are to conſider, that in the former Sway, when <hi>French</hi> Counſels and <hi>French Gold</hi> reigned too Potent, Your Lordſhip thought Your ſelf a very unqualified Engliſh Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tier in a Court ſo little an <hi>Engliſh One,</hi> and 'tis perhaps Your Higheſt Glory, to have no ſooner a Call to Glory.</p>
            <p>But, alas! Your Lordſhips Hiſtorian is not my Province; 'tis enough to have choſen a Patriot for a Patron, and to pride my ſelf in this occaſion of publiſhing my ſelf,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt Devoted, Obedient Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>AFter ſo many Years Vaſſalage to <hi>France,</hi> our too long and too Scandalous <hi>Dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neracy,</hi> Providence having at laſt raiſed us the fair Hopes of being <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> once more, I make my <hi>True Britiſh</hi> Reader no diſacceptable Preſent in the Contents of this Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, unfolding the Great <hi>Myſtery of Iniquity,</hi> the true <hi>Extract</hi> and <hi>Generation</hi> of our Great Diſturber of the World, <hi>Lewis XIV.</hi> But though this Narrative may be ſomewhat Novel here, it has been the Univerſal Outcry of <hi>France.</hi> The known <hi>Frigidity</hi> of <hi>Lewis XIII.</hi> and the Birth of this <hi>Deodat,</hi> ſo called, after 23 years Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs Marriage, with all other attending Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, ſo plainly convincing the <hi>Impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility</hi> of his being his Reputed Royal Father's Begetting, that nothing but the Forehead of a <hi>Legender</hi> muſt pretend it. The famous <hi>Barri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cado of Paris,</hi> and ſo formidable a <hi>Revolt</hi> under ſuch Great Leaders againſt him, at his firſt Acceſſion to the Throne, too publickly proclaimed his <hi>Extraneous Birth,</hi> inſomuch that all Tongues were full of it, Reaſon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed it, and ſcarce a Doubt or Scruple to queſtion it. 'Tis true, indeed, His <hi>Canine Teeth</hi> and the <hi>French Slavery</hi> growing up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, ſo bold and ſo dangerous a Truth was a
<pb facs="tcp:31510:5"/> little huſh'd, and durſt talk no louder than in the Whiſpers and Murmurs of Cloſets. And if any critical Reader ſhould ask why this Hiſtory ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw Light in <hi>England</hi> till now, let him but <hi>think</hi> when he moves that Queſtion, and he will ſoon anſwer himſelf, by conſidering, that in the two laſt <hi>French-penſion</hi> Reigns, when <hi>Cole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> told <hi>Le Chaiſe [The Intereſt of My Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Yours are inſeparable]</hi> the very At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of ſo hideous a Profanation againſt our then adored <hi>Idol</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> our <hi>Grand Maſter Lewis</hi> had pull'd down that inevitable Thunder againſt ſo capital a Tranſgreſſor, as had undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly raiſed both <hi>Publiſher</hi> and <hi>Printer</hi> a higher Gibbet than <hi>Hamans.</hi> For Inſtance of which, a Paper but a little inclining this way, only in ſome Minute Reflections upon the Birth of <hi>Lewis,</hi> our preſent Theme, was about the latter end of King <hi>Charles's</hi> Reign burnt at <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Croſs</hi> by the common Hangman, and the Impreſſion ſuppreſs'd. And if the Proſecution ſtop'd there, 'twas more for the politick <hi>huſhing</hi> of the <hi>Subject</hi> of the Paper, than in any Mercy to the <hi>Author</hi> or <hi>Promoter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now after this full and thorough Search into the Cradle of our Son of Thunder, <hi>Lewis,</hi> after examining the <hi>Neſt,</hi> the <hi>Egg,</hi> the <hi>Brooding</hi> and the <hi>Hatching;</hi> though the whole Conduct of his Reign has been ſo much the Subject of Humane <hi>Amazement</hi> and <hi>Horror,</hi> I muſt do him this publick Right, as to own I am not ſo much ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled
<pb facs="tcp:31510:5"/> as the reſt of the fooliſh World may be. For example, to ſurvey him round, what if, in the firſt place, Hiſtory or Chronicle have rarely or never afforded his <hi>Match</hi> in Breach of <hi>Treaties</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, or <hi>Oaths</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> at home? For let us conſider him as he is: Why ſhould we ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>His</hi> Honour any Stronger than his <hi>Mothers! Impoſture</hi> was his Foundation, and <hi>Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Treachery</hi> run in his Veins. What Wonder then that he ſhould <hi>Reign</hi> in <hi>Perjury,</hi> when he was <hi>Begot</hi> in it? <hi>Infidelity</hi> govern'd the whole Aſcendant at his <hi>Conception,</hi> and the continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of its Influence ever ſince, is only to make his <hi>Life</hi> of a piece with his <hi>Nativity;</hi> and the <hi>Wielding</hi> of his Scepter an <hi>Original</hi> like his Means of <hi>Gaining</hi> it. <hi>But then he takes De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in ſhamefully</hi> Falſifying <hi>and</hi> Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breaking <hi>with Sovereign Heads</hi>—Yes; <hi>Royalty</hi> is no <hi>Kin</hi> to him; and therefore his <hi>Averſion.</hi> The <hi>Cannibal</hi> never devours a <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibal,</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> preys upon Princes, becauſe they are <hi>Aliens</hi> and <hi>Heterogenes</hi> to Himſelf. I confeſs however there is yet one Prince in the World at leaſt, that our <hi>Lewis</hi> has ſome kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs for. And ſtrong cauſe why: For he was <hi>learning</hi> after his own <hi>Copy,</hi> to keep Faith as little as Himſelf, and as once ſo hopeful a <hi>Profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient</hi> under ſo Great a <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> he loves him for ſome little <hi>Likeneſs-ſake. But then what's more Monſtrous, he Leagues with</hi> Mahomet-Yes, his Engagement with the <hi>Turk</hi> againſt
<pb facs="tcp:31510:6"/> 
               <hi>Chriſtendom</hi> is a little <hi>Notorious,</hi> and the <hi>Alcoran</hi> is more in his Favour than the <hi>Bible.</hi> And good Reaſon. For <hi>That</hi> will never riſe up in Judgment againſt him, though <hi>This</hi> ſhall. Though he has made bold to crack a ſmall <hi>Oath,</hi> when he Swore to the <hi>Edict</hi> of <hi>Nants;</hi> and another <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Sacrament</hi> that he would never invade <hi>Flanders,</hi> &amp;c. He was never For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworn upon the <hi>Alcoran,</hi> though he has been up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Evangeliſts. 'Tis true the Clamours of</hi> Europe <hi>are juſtly loud againſt him for the</hi> Sanguinary Principles <hi>and</hi> unprecedented Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elties <hi>of the hard-mouth'd</hi> Lewis—But for my part it is a leſs Subject of my Admiration, when my little Reading in <hi>Phyſicks</hi> leads me to conſider that thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> in him, and that <hi>Propenſity to Blood</hi> lye only at <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture's</hi> Door. Do we not daily ſee the very ſame natural Inclinations predominant even in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior Animals? What treacherous ill nature ſhall we find in a <hi>Mungril,</hi> compared with the Generoſity of a True Begotten Maſtiff?</p>
            <p>One Advertiſement I muſt give my Reader, <hi>viz.</hi> That our young <hi>Monſieur Legrand,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards dignified the <hi>Chevalier de Roan</hi> (whom in reſpect to his exalted Fortunes in his Royal Miſtreſſes Favours, I rather mention by his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle than his Name) has not here finiſh'd his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory: The fatal Cataſtrophe of that poor Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, the Tragick Concluſion of his Dear bought Pleaſures, being reſerved for a ſecond Volum.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:31510:6"/>
            <head>The Amours of <hi>Anne</hi> (Queen to <hi>Lewis XIII.</hi>) with the <hi>Chevalier de Roan,</hi> true Father to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent <hi>Lewis XIV.</hi> King of <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HIſtorians have but too loudly, and too infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly recorded the long uſurp'd Dominion and Aſcendance of the Triple Diadem over the Scepters of Temporal Princes; an Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition obtained only by the implicit Reſignation of the too bigotted Diſciples of Infallibility, whoſe ſtrength of Romiſh Faith overpowring their weaker Royal Reaſon, has ſometimes ſubjected their Thrones to a Vaſſalage almoſt as intire as that of their Souls. But this is not ſo much to be wondred at, ſince Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks even of a lower ſtation, and of inferiour Dignity to that of their mighty Lord the Pope, have ſometimes been little leſs than ſole Adminiſtrators Supreme; whilſt not only the whole Helm of States has been guided by them, but alſo the whole Regalia of Power have been ſo totally lodged in their own Hands, till the ſubminiſtring depending Monarchs, their kind Reſigners, have been little more than Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tular. An inſtance of which, perhaps, was never more famous, than in the French Adminiſtration of the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> under, or rather over <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. That fatal [<hi>Ego, &amp; Rex meus, I and my King</hi>] ſo vainly and ſo unhappily arrogated by the unfortunate Engliſh <hi>Woolſey,</hi> (that memorably glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:31510:7"/> Butchers Son, who had kneeling Nobility for his Cup-beaters) was a truer and more conſpicuous Jewel in the greater and happier <hi>Richlieu</hi>'s Cardinals Cap; whilſt no exalted Favourite poſſibly ever govern'd more abſolute than himſelf. And to fix this glorious Blazon in his Scutcheon, perhaps it had a double Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter. Firſt, The exorbitant Favour of <hi>Mary de Medicis,</hi> ſometimes Queen Regent, during the Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII. that introduced and advanced him to all that Grandeur: And next, the poor ſpirited Weakneſs of <hi>Lewis</hi> himſelf, that even after his Arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val at Manhood, only changing the Regency from <hi>Mary</hi> to <hi>Richlieu,</hi> continued ſtill under the Cardinal's Guardianſhip, either not willing, not daring, or not able (or all of them) to reſume the unlimited Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority that that great Miniſter had ſo long poſſeſt.</p>
            <p>And as true Greatneſs is only perfectly eſtabliſh'd, where no Controul or Oppoſition can ſhake it, this Reigning Favourite had all the kindeſt Smiles of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to gild his Brow; for his Sovereignty over the Will of the King was not greater than the Dominion he held in the Favour of the Queen too, the Royal Conſort, <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>A.</hi> The Affections and pleaſure of his generous Royal Miſtris, were ſo much under the Guide and Government of <hi>Richlieu,</hi> that the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal was her moſt truſted Cabinet Counſellor. Thus, in fine, with no ſuperiour Influence to malign him, nor Equal to rival him, with the Hearts of all with him or above him, and the Knees of all below him, his Power ſtood fixt, and his Foundation immovable. In this high ſtation he grew ſo popular, and withal ſo aſpiring, that together with the Exaltation of his perſonal Honours, his Soul was no leſs elevated too; Inſomuch that he wanted not an over-large Taint of that common Contagion of Dignity, <hi>Pride.</hi> The Sanctity of his Spiritual Robe, alas! was no Fence againſt it, whilſt Ambition, with all its attendant Vanities and Frailties ſo wholly poſſeſt our great Lord Cardinal, that the Church-man was entirely loſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:31510:7"/> in the Governing States-man, and his Eccleſiaſtical Scarlet wholly truckled to his ſairer and all com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding Royal Purple, with which his propirious Fortune had ſo ſignally inveſted him.</p>
            <p>Under the Umbrage of our great <hi>Richlieu,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent talleſt Cedar of the Grove, ſprung a fair <hi>Scion</hi> from ſo nouriſhing a Root, a beautiful Niece; who favour'd and cheriſh'd by ſo potent a Patron, and ſo near a Relation, made one of the brighteſt and moſt glittering Court Stars of <hi>France;</hi> a Lady in her Perſon, Mein, and Ayre ſo extraordinary charming, as could not ſail of a whole train of Hearts. To match theſe outward dazling Charms, Nature had no leſs richly furniſh'd her within, <hi>viz.</hi> with that ſprightly Wit and refined Senſe, as ſpoke her Miſtreſs of a Soul no ways unworthy ſo fair a Lodging. 'Tis true, indeed, ſhe had a natural Pride, and an unbounded Ambition; but thoſe, as hereditary Qualifications, derived from <hi>Richlieu,</hi> and which (whatever Faults elſewhere) in the preſent Eſtimate of the World, are reputed Vertues in the fair Sex, were rather her Ornament than Blemiſh.</p>
            <p>This young Lady, the Darling of <hi>Richlieu,</hi> (under the Tutelage of his peculiar Care and Protection, you may imagin) had no ſplendor nor Pomp wanting to bear that Port, and render her that Figure in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> to the higheſt that either Beauty deſerved, or almoſt Vanity could wiſh. And as if her Alliance to the Cardinal had entituled her to ſhare a part of his Trophies, and Rule where he Reigned, ſhe had gained ſo far upon the Favour of the kind Queen, ſo careſs'd and ſo loved by her, that the Queen had ſcarce that Secret which ſhe lodged not in the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom of this fair Favourite; ſo fond of her Company, and ſo wedded to her Converſation, that ſhe could hardly reliſh a Pleaſure without her. To ſtyle her the Queens Confident and Friend, is a Name of too narrow a comprehenſion: their endearments were ſo extravagant, that ſhe treated her more like a Siſter.
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:31510:8"/> And that Court Ceremony and formal State might be no bar to their more particular Intimacy and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarity, the Queen was generouſly pleaſed to give her ſelf the Romantick Name of <hi>Statira,</hi> and her fair Confident, <hi>Pariſatis;</hi> (Titles borrowed from the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Daughters of the great <hi>Perſian Darius</hi>) with an abſolute Command laid upon her in all their private Entertainments and Converſe to uſe no other Names between them; that the Title of Majeſty, or the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomary reſpect, and more awful Diſtance to a Crowned Head might be no impediment to that nearer Liberty, and freer Ayre and Gayety ſhe deſired in the Friendſhip and Society of her deareſt <hi>Pariſatis.</hi> Our fair <hi>Pariſatis</hi> (for ſince that Name had the honour of a Royal Donation, we cannot give her a better) had her natural Pride in no ſmall meaſure heightned from her ſtanding ſo fair in theſe extraordinary good Graces of ſo Royal a Patroneſs, as borrowing no ſmall Additional Luſtre from that ſtation and ſphere. For ſhe could not think that the envious World could imagin her to receive ſuch unaccountable Favours, without ſome extraordinary Mine of Vertue to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve them. Thus, beſides the Attraction of her own ſingular Merits, with ſuch Crouds of Suitors, and daily Court made to her, ſo many of the Supplicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the Queen being addreſt to <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> ſhe looked upon her ſelf as a ſmall Saint to a Deity, enrich'd with no common Emanations of Glory (for Court Favourites ſhine by Reflection) from ſo Divine a Fountain of it.</p>
            <p>With all theſe careſſing Smiles of Honour on her ſide, the faireſt golden Lot of Fortune ſo proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly drawn, <hi>Love</hi> only has his laſt Game to play, which if a lucky one, muſt now give her the only re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining Conſummation of Felicity. Adorers ſuch Beauty cannot want, for <hi>Cupid</hi> might be proud to empty a whole Quiver in her Cauſe. But whatever ſilent Vows were paid her, in all the random ſhot ſhe daily made among the Herd of unworthier Slaves, as
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:31510:8"/> they are Objects all below her thoughts, ſo nothing but the higheſt and nobleſt Quality muſt dare to be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenders to the Glory of wearing her Chains. The only wounded Heart ſhe can vouchſafe to pity, muſt have no other Recommendation than the Higheſt Princely Veins to center in it. For as we told you, Ambition ruled her whole Aſcendant; inſtead of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Courage, Wit, Gallantry, Paſſion, Fidelity, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, thoſe inſide and outſide Qualifications that uſually prefer the Faithful Lover to the eaſier Ladies Favour; High Blood only anſwers all with the aſpiring <hi>Pariſatis;</hi> and no Oblation or Incenſe burns hallowed or fragrant without it. In ſhort, Love muſt lead her to a Palace before he gets her into a Temple; for truly ſhe takes her only proſpect of Happineſs from Turrets and Battlements, and her Bridal Pillow can only lye ſoft where the Bed is Imperial.</p>
            <p>Amongſt her numerous Captives (not to mention any of her inferior Conqueſts, which, as not thought worthy her own Cognizance, ſhall be as little worthy ours) to gratifie the Ambition of our towring <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatis,</hi> it fell out, that no leſs than the Monſieur, the King's own Brother, <hi>Gaſton,</hi> Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come her moſt paſſionate Admirer. The moſt ardent Devoirs, with a thouſand Vows and Proteſtations, were daily laid at her Feet by this Royal Inamorato. His whole Orizons were paid to no other Saint, and the Praiſes of her Beauty, and the Effects of its Power, at all Opportunities ſtudiouſly ſought, were chanted in her Ears by ſo aſſiduous a Servant. The p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ed <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> no doubt, wanted no liſtening Ear to ſo Illuſtrious a Lover, and though with all the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> and diſtance, ſuitable even to the Character of a <hi>Clelia</hi> or a <hi>Caſſandra,</hi> ſhe received his Addreſſes under all the moſt rigid Laws and Obligations of Feminine Honour, and with all the formal Coldneſs of her Sex, ſhe had nevertheleſs a private Satisfaction which gave her no little warmth within, from the Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that courting Glory, which ſhe ſaw bent
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:31510:9"/> low before her, as ſo humble a Suppliant for her Ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptance. She look'd upon him not only as the Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the King, a Title of it ſelf alone ſufficient to build his fair hopes of Succeſs, and her own fairer Foundation of Happineſs upon; but alſo at preſent the Heir Preſumptive (if not Apparent) of the Crown of <hi>France.</hi> For as his unperforming Brother, the King, (alas!) had now lain more than twenty long ineffectual years by the ſide of her charming <hi>Statira,</hi> and his Fair <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>A</hi>—there was very little or no interpoſing Danger of a young Dauphin, from that Fair but uncultivated Field of Love, to bar the Monſieur's Inheritance of Empire: And con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently the proſpect of a Diadem glittering in her Fancy, and the poſſibility of her living to be Queen of <hi>France,</hi> infuſed no mean Inclinations in Favour of <hi>Orleans.</hi> And though, 'tis true, it lay only in the Breaſt of Providence, whether <hi>Orleans</hi> were deſtined to ſurvive his Brother, and reach that Crown; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if ſhe lived not to be Wife of a King, ſhe might probably be the Mother of one. For as <hi>Gaſton</hi> had given the World a more pregnant Teſtimony of his Manhood, than his imbeciler Flegmatick Brother, made already a happy Father, yet his fair Offſpring being of the Female Sex, and therefore by the Salick Law excluded from Imperial Succeſſion, it might poſſibly be ordained, ſhe fancied (and even Virgin Fancy may ſometimes rove to Motherly thoughts) her own peculiar Glory and Bleſſing (though ſhe wore it not her ſelf) to bear from her own Veins an Heir to a Diadem, and perhaps to ſee him wear it too. In concluſion, how long a Chain of thoughts on this fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Theme, and what pleaſing Conceptions preſented themſelves to her Meditations upon her preſent gawdy Fortune in view, the Spirit of <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> or at leaſt a Soul of her own Dimenſion, can only imagine.</p>
            <p>The Addreſs of our inamour'd <hi>Orleans,</hi> as an Affair ſo nearly relating to her Dear <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> was kept no Secret to the Queen; and indeed there was no matter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:31510:9"/> of Privacy in it, the Queen being really an original Confident in ſo viſible an Amour: for there was ſcarce that Acceſs to be gotten to <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> but what was in the preſence of the Queen; ſo induſtriouſly ſhe avoided all other Opportunities, as there was rarely a moments Interview between the paſſionate <hi>Orleans</hi> and her ſelf, that had not her ſacred Eye and Ear a Witneſs of all that paſs'd between 'em; ſo cautiouſly had the wiſe <hi>Pariſatis</hi> managed ſo important a Treaty of Love. But as neither the Queens preſence, nor indeed any thing elſe could baulk our Monſieur's amorous Perſuit of his Miſtreſs, his emboldened Profeſſions were under no Reſtraint, avowing before the Queen, his intire Devotion and Captivity to the conquering Eyes of her beloved Darling, and his own adored <hi>Pariſatis.</hi> The Queen, whoſe Zeal for her <hi>Pariſatis</hi> Advancement, had made her an inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſted Party, took the occaſion very often to applaud the Monſieur's choice in the diſpoſal of his Heart, aſſuring him that both her Wit and Charms were ſo highly deſerving, that he could not ſit down in a nobler Siege; and if his Heart were anſwerable to his Vows and Profeſſions, he ſhould not want her beſt friendly Offices to promote any Honourable Preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to a Lady, who beſides her own ponderous Merits and Attractions, had Her Richeſt Royal Favour, an unalienable part of her Dowry, to fill up the Scale. The Monſieur, to expreſs his high Satisfaction from her Majeſties Gracious Inclinations towards him, always returned her his humble and moſt profound Acknowledgments, continuing ſtill to launch out into all the moſt extravagant Praiſes and Raptures that Wit or Eloquence could furniſh on ſo copious a Theme as the Beauties and Charms of his <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> avowing himſelf her eternal Devote.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal, who had not yet publickly appeared in this Affair, was nevertheleſs all this while a moſt attentive Liſtner behind the Curtain, as no indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Zealot for his Nieces Preferment. And ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:31510:10"/> being called to a private Conſult with the Queen, after ſome General Reflections on the Glory of ſo Noble a Match for her deareſt <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with not only her beſt Services, but alſo her promiſe of engaging the King too, if neceſſary, in her Cauſe (to which the Cardinal expreſs'd his moſt dutiful Senſe of ſo Royal an Obligation) the Queen began to make a full Repetition of all the Court the Monſieur had made to his Niece; but upon full Scrutiny and Deſcant upon the whole, ſhe remarked, that <hi>Orleans,</hi> 'tis true, had all along been ſo exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tantly paſſionate in his Vows and Proteſtations, that if his Language ſpoke his Soul, there could not be a more captivated Lover than himſelf. But all this while he had never yet come to a particular Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, his Courtſhip hitherto had only expreſs'd it ſelf in Generals, in Harangues upon her Beauty, and his Fetters, with all the Cuſtomary Love-Flouriſhes, the uſual Preliminary Gallantries of an Amorous Suitor, and that was all. He had yet rather endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured the rendring his own Love acceptable, than ſupplicated any particular Return of Hers, having never yet come to the Peremptory Queſtion, Marriage. And though 'tis true, as far as Decency would permit, her zealous Friendſhip for his Niece had prompted the Generous Queen ſometimes to hint to him the Merit of ſo Beautiful a Bride; and 'tis true, the Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur had always made anſwer with that Tranſport as declared how grateful ſo pleaſing a ſound was to him, yet he had not made the leaſt direct Application to <hi>Pariſatis</hi> or the Queen (though offer'd her Interceſſion in it) tending that way.</p>
            <p>This Obſervation afforded matter of Debate: As firſt, That the Monſieur was a Perſon that had not only more innate Honour, but alſo more Years upon his Back, than to make ſo publick (for now the whole Court rung of it) and ſo ſerious a Suit to a Young Lady, and yet not really to be in earneſt. For Rallery or Amuſement to ſo notorious a Prejudice to a Virgin
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:31510:10"/> Ladies Reputation, too Sacred to be jeſted withal in ſuch a manner, was a thing the Monſieur neither would nor could be guilty of. So that the Truth and Reality of his Love was paſt all Doubt or Diſpute. But then again, if ſo violent a Lover, as his repeated Oaths had ſworn for him, what Bar lay in his way to hinder him coming to the finiſhing Interrogatory? His Courtſhip had now been the Buſineſs of conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Time; and tedious Woings are only fit for Lovers of humble Merit, ſuch who have poſſibly no other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commendation than their Whining and Dying at a La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies Feet, and conſequently through long Services and longer Penance, muſt make a Pilgrimage of it to a Ladies Heart: But the Monſieur's Caſe was quite diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, he was Brother to a King, and viſible Heir to a Crown. His very Character and Birth therefore com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioned his Bolder Advance, and made ſo ſtrong a Plea for him, that his Approach lay fairer and nearer without all this idle Ceremony, and unneceſſary For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality; a Vanity likewiſe generally unpractiſed by Perſons of his Age and Experience, who having been a Husband before, if for no other reaſon, they thought might have launcht forward with more Confidence, and arrived at the deciding Concluſion, without all this lingering woing Pain and Toil. Nay, what was odder yet, and ſeemed a little unaccountable, though even prompted by the Queen to the determinating Period, his Anſwers ſtill rambled wide from the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and always waved that Subject.</p>
            <p>Upon ſumming up the whole, the Queen came to this Advice, That as Matters ſtood, the Cardinal ſhould take a favourable Opportunity, in the preſence of ſome of the Nobles of <hi>France,</hi> after his Thanks for the Honour the Monſieur had done him in his kind Ircll<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations towards his Niece, frankly to make a tender of Marriage to him; a part ſo becoming the Cardinal in paternal care of his Niece; and conſidering the high Extract of the Monſieur, no ways below him to be the firſt Aggreſſor; nay, and which perhaps might all
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:31510:11"/> this while have been the only real occaſion of the Monſieur's Heſitation, as expecting it from him; it being not impoſſible, his Pride, as a Prince of the Blood Royal, might look for that Gratification, nor was it unreaſonable for the Cardinal to give it him. This Counſel, as it carried the Face of Reaſon, was heartily and thankfully embraced by the Cardinal; and for that favourable Opportunity, deſired, he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed the making of a ſplendid Ball at his own Palace, to which inviting their Majeſties, the Monſieur, and the whole Court, in the midſt of all his Hoſpitality and Entertainment, he ſhould lay hold of ſome kind Minute to make him the Tender propoſed, under his own Roof. The Queen highly applanded the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection of <hi>Richlieu,</hi> and the Conſult terminating in this Reſolve, the Fair <hi>Pariſatis</hi> was called to give her Aſſent to it, who readily and dutifully ſubmitting to the undiſputed Pleaſure and Will of the Queen and the Cardinal, intirely reſigned the Diſpoſal of her ſelf, and the Ordination of her Fate, to their abſolute Decretals.</p>
            <p>Accordingly a Ball is made at the Cardinal's, with all the Gallantry and Magnificence ſuitable to the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of an entertaining Prelate, where a full Conſtella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the Court-ſtars, the whole luſtre of <hi>France,</hi> ſhined together. But to recite what Faces amongſt ſo many rivalling Ladies carried the preference, or how far our <hi>Pariſatis</hi> was a leading Beauty amongſt them, being not material to our Hiſtory, we have on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to remark, that a Noble young Gentleman, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Stranger in Court, but afterwards known by the-Name of the <hi>Chevalier de Roan,</hi> appearing in this Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Aſſembly, made the moſt eminent Figure there, and drew the Eyes of both Sexes upon him His extraordinary Perſonage, his gallant Mein and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porment, and what added an Ornament to the reſt, as being the peculiar Grace at this time and place, his excellent performance in Dancing, recommend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to the general admiration of the whole Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:31510:11"/> and conferr'd upon him beſide, the particular Honour of being ſingled out to dance with the Queen, as due to his own ſingular merit; a favour at ſuch a ſeaſon, and in ſo gay a Court as that of <hi>France,</hi> not always given to pre-eminence in Title or Blood.</p>
            <p>In the height of their entertainment, whilſt the youn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger and the gayer Revellers were taken up as Spectators or Performers in this Princely Scene of Delight, their Eyes, or their Heels, (or both) employed, it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that <hi>Gaſton,</hi> having had enough of that airier Treat, had ſelected out half a dozen of the Grandees of <hi>France,</hi> and reſolving to ſee what more ſubſtantial Chear and Hoſpitality he could find within, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired into one of the with-drawing Rooms, where ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſumptuous Banquets of Sweetmeats were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared, ſet forth in all the richeſt ſtate imaginable. The Cardinal, whoſe Eye and Thought attended the Monſieur, was inſtantly one amongſt them, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented the Prince, and his few, but noble Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, with all the Civilities and Careſſes that might be expected at all times from a Perſon of ſo much Addreſs as <hi>Richlieu,</hi> more eſpecially on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, where it was introductory to a Parley of ſuch Importance.</p>
            <p>After a brisk Glaſs or two of Wine had gon about, enricht each round with a ſeveral Noble Health, it fell out at laſt in the Circle to one of the Noble-men's chance to begin Madam the Cardinal's Nieces Health, poſſibly more in complement to their generous Hoſt, the Lord of the Feaſt, as being his Relation than in any Thought that concerned the <hi>Monſieur</hi> as her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant. The Cardinal well pleaſed to have her Name firſt ſtarted by a ſecond hand, laid hold of the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to apply himſelf to the <hi>Monſieur</hi> in a very elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Speech, acknowledging (in all the moſt obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>) the ſignal Glory that ſhined upon him, as a particular Donation of the Prince, in his gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and Inclinations for what was ſo near to him both in Relation and Protection, as his Niece.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:31510:12"/> And that all his preſent return in part of Diſcharge of ſo vaſt an Obligation loaded upon him from ſo high an Honour, was only his own and his Niece's du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Reſignation to the pleaſure of the Prince; and in farther gratification to his Honourable Pretenſions, by vertue of his own Authority over her, (to which her Obedience muſt acquieſce) to tender her in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to him; which in all Humility he accordingly offered him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Monſieur,</hi> who from the Cardinal's firſt entrance upon this Subject, began to glow extremely, his Face redning all the while at no ſmall rate, attended (with what patience may be imagined by the ſequel) the end of his Speech; when coming to the propoſal of Marriage, all his return was in this ſhort Anſwer, <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, Proud Prieſt!</hi> ſeconded with a hearty Box of the Ear beſtowed upon him with no little indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The attending French Nobles were ſtruck with no common aſtoniſhment and confuſion at ſo amazing a Rupture. The Aſtront of a Blow given to the Prime Miniſter the great Superintendant of State in the Poſt and Power of <hi>Richleiu,</hi> being matter for ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Surprize. But as the Greatneſs of both their Qualities ſtood too high for any particular Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of theirs, all their part was only to expreſs their general Concern and Diſorder, and to endeavour to withdraw the Monſieur. Accordingly they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly requeſted him to retire home by the Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtairs, without publickly diſturbing of the Aſſembly within, by that certain Uproar which the leaſt Breath from this Air would unavoidably raiſe amongſt them. The Prince prevailed upon by that Conſideration, accepted their Counſel, and retired, only with two or three hearty Oaths muttered at his drawing off, <hi>That his Niece and himſelf might have come to a right underſtanding without reading ſo hard a Chapter as</hi> Marriage, <hi>and honour enough too done his Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renceſhips Church-blood, as High and as Proud as he was</hi>—Whether theſe laſt words of the Monſieurs
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:31510:12"/> were heard or no, we are not informed; but truly it matters little, his Soul being full enough of thoſe three hard Words that came before, and the harder Blow that came with them: And indeed the Senſe of this laſt part of the Princes Declaration was too plainly contained in the foregoing ſhort, but compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive Sentence. His diſdainful Refuſal of his Niece in Marriage, with the Storm that followed it, but too manifeſtly publiſhing what ſort of Love the Monſieur drove at in his Courtſhip to that Young Lady.</p>
            <p>What Reſentments, or rather what Agonies the Cardinal felt at this Affront, I ſhall not ſo much endeavour to deſcribe, the whole Sequel of our Hiſtory, being indeed only the violent Motions from this one Mortal Ferment. It is enough to tell you that Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latick Honour, <hi>alias</hi> Spiritual Pride, was wounded in the tendereſt Part, and bore all the Pangs of ſo pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trating a Stab. And as the higheſt Revenge is the natural Product of ſo provoking an Injury, you muſt expect from this one Minutes fertile Seeds, the Brood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Work for Years of Miſchief; and to find our Man of Heaven poſſeſs'd with half the Furies of Hell, with ſo much as every Snake and every Sting about them. But as deep a Mine of Sulphur as this Fire brand had lighted in the Cardinal's Breaſt, he was nevertheleſs ſo much Maſter of his Temper, as not to ſtart out into too ſudden or flaſhy a Rage, his Vengeance being reſerved for more certain and therefore more deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berate Execution. And accordingly, returning to the Noble Company, he forced a Complaiſance, which for the ſhort remainder of the Entertainment, ſhrouded all his Diſcontent under the faireſt Face he could put on. And the Witneſſes of his Diſgrace being all at preſent departed, it was a means to huſh all, at leaſt ſo long as till the Ball was over. But no ſooner had this Accident taken Air (which was in few hours after) and the whole Court began to be loud with it, but the Cardinal, to be neither Idle
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:31510:13"/> nor Ungrateful, for a ſmall Earneſt of better Payment, the firſt work he did, was to paint the ſhort Hiſtory of laſt nights Adventures in ſuch Colours to the King, that the Monſieur's Baniſhment from Court was the next Mornings firſt Diſpatch before his upriſing.</p>
            <p>From the King's Bed-Chamber his next ſtep was to his Nieces, who, poor Lady, partly through the Fatigue of laſt nights Dancing, and likewiſe ſome little Thoughtfulneſs after her waking, relating to the expected kind Anſwer of the Monſicur to the Cardinal, which detained her ſome time longer in Bed, (neither Dreaming laſt night, nor fancying on her Pillow this Morning, any leſs than an honourable Reply, ſuitable to the Violence of his Paſſion, and the Force of her own Charms,) was but newly riſen, and Heaven knows, as yet, wholly Ignorant of the fatal Schriech-Owl Notes approaching her: For alas! though long before this, the meaneſt Attendant about her, nay, the pooreſt Servant in the Family, had the whole Diſmal Tale almoſt old and ſtale amongſt them; yet as ungrateful Sounds come generally laſt to the unhappy Ears that are moſt concerned in them, the ſad Narrative is reſerved for the Cardinal's firſt Delivery.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal accordingly entring her Chamber, took his Niece alone, and gave her the whole Story at large, aggravated by all the keeneſt Bitterneſs of Spirit, in the manner and Circumſtances of the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Our <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> who attended the laſt Syllable of it, without interpoſing one word (her Soul indeed being too full for a haſty vent) after the Cardinal had compleatly finiſh'd the matter of Fact, together with ſome Additional Remarks of his own, dreſs'd up in that Language which the moſt poynant Gall and radi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated Spight could furniſh him; ſhe broke out at laſt into this following Reply. <hi>O Monſter! Monſter! Infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del! I have been woed then all this while only to make a Whore of! Traytor! Villain! A Toy reſerved to play with at his idle Hours. Alas! the generous Monſieur deſigned
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:31510:13"/> Honour for me. A little poor low deſpicable thing as I am, by his moſt Gracious condeſcending Favour, decreed the Glorious Exaltation of being the High and Mighty</hi> Orleans'<hi>s private Divertiſement. Goat! Satyr! Devil!</hi> Then muſing a while ſhe continued, <hi>What Shame and what Confuſion is deſtined for poor miſerable me? Had he but plaid the honeſt bare-fac'd Villain, and at his firſt Addreſs frankly ſpoke out his Leud Laſcivious Suit, and plainly told his execrable purpoſe, I could have met the Monſter with that Look and Treatment he deſerved; and at his very firſt Aſſault have thundered my Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in his hardened Face, and made the Ecchoing World a Witneſs of my Scorn and Indignation. But the baſe Gozener, the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nprincely Poor Impoſtor has worn the Golden Vizor and betray'd me, betray'd my credulous Ear; ſeduced my cheated Reaſon ſo egregiouſly, that I have heard him, heard him with Patience, ſuffered him my Preſence, and bore the treacherous Sounds of his vile Love repeated o'er and o'er. And what will babbling Fame and the miſ-judging World, to think that I have hearkened ſo long and loath'd no ſooner, but Record me for a Liſtener, a downright Favourer of his lawleſs Suit pleaſed with the fultry Breath; whilſt thus my injured Virgin-Innocence muſt ſtand the Blaſt of each pollutin Tongue, and all my Honour Canker into Infamy; when common Story, and every laughing Varlet ſhall jeſt upon my Shame</hi>—Here the Cardinal began to interrupt her, endeavouring to pacifie at leaſt that part of her Reſentment, by aſſuring her, that both her Conduct and his own in this matter, as ſenſeleſs as popular Miſtakes and Follies may be, ſhould ſoon convince the World as to that Point, and remove all ſhadow of ſo mean an Imputation, and ſo ſordid a Blemiſh upon the Virtue of his Niece; and that no danger of Reproach or Slander ſhould threaten her then. <hi>Well then,</hi> replied <hi>Parifatis, ſuppoſe the World will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me the Right as to clear my Innocence and Virtue at le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> from that one Scandal, and as a ſpecial mark of the Juſtice, only give me my due, in publiſhing me that wea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:31510:14"/> that ſhallow, bubbled, cudden'd Fool (for that's the beſt of my Names) as could hear an inſolent uninterrupted Villain, buzzing ſo long, ſo loud, and ſo often in my Ear, without either Wit or Senſe enough to underſtand him all this while. Alas! Sir, what if I ſcape this Calumny, ſurmounting one Billow while another ſinks me? Oh! do but think, but ſeriouſly conſider what a Deluge and Inua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of irreſiſtible Shame will overwhelm me, when I muſt ever bear about me, and carry to my Grave a Name ſo little; pointed and hiſt at by reviling Tongues, as a poor courſe-born Creature ſought only for a Harlot; a wretched thing, thought worthy of no higher than the looſe Pleaſures of the Monſieur. Oh! that accurſed fixt eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtain! Which not the Blood of that ungrateful Man can ever waſh away. The Beauty of a Subject has ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conquered Kings, and the Daughters of common Nobility have been often raiſed to the Beds and Thrones of the greateſt of Monarchs. But the poor harder-fated little humble Niece of</hi> Richlieu <hi>has neither Beauty, Blood nor Merit, worth an honorable Thought from the Younger Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of</hi> Lewis, <hi>that Lucifer Devil of Pride,</hi> Orleans. Nay, ſhe ſo much undeſerved ſo exalted a Favour, that the very Motion of it could be repulſed with no leſs a Contempt, than treating the Great Cardinal <hi>Richlieu</hi> with the Indignity of a Groom or Varlet, the Reward of an impudent vile Blow, a Buffet for a Vagabond. <hi>But, Sir, I hope ſuch Injuries as mine, this Outrage of a rude Barbarian, acted upon a poor young Virgins bleeding Fame, ſo near to you in Blood (and I hope nearer to your Heart) this ruining blaſting load of my Diſhonour, cries loud for Vengeance from you. Yes, my poor Child,</hi> replied the Cardinal, <hi>doubt not but I ſhall be thine and my own Avenger. Alas! dear injured Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, my Fever burns as violently as thine, though I do not talk my pain ſo loud as thou doſt: For this Barbarian (as thou juſtly calleſt him) has acted Outrage on my Honour too; and I have that long heavy Score of Juſtice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> account and ballance with him, that if I ſhew him Mercy, may Heaven never ſhew me any.</hi>—Our
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:31510:14"/> 
               <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> at the Cardinal's ſo hearty a Promiſe of Revenge, was ready to imbrace his very Knees in gratitude for ſo pleaſing an Accent: Even the thought whereof was ſuch an Alleviation to the Torments and Anguiſh of her Soul, as changed the very Air of her Face; inſomuch that with all the gayeſt and ſprite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt Raptures and Applauſes as due to ſo glorious a Reſolution; ſhe call'd him the beſt of Friends, the kindeſt of Fathers, her Sacred Champion, her Tutelar Angel (no Name was too Good for him) Her Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port could hardly forbear giving him more than Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Attributes; ſuch Divine Muſick to her, was the very ſound of Vengeance.</p>
            <p>Their private Conference was now interrupted by a Viſit of the Queens, who having both heard and felt the Injuries of her dear <hi>Parifatis,</hi> was kindly come her own Embaſſadreſs, with the Compliments of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolance on ſo ſad an Occaſion. The Queen ſoon bore a part in the mournful Chorus, and expreſs'd her ſelf in ſo many juſt Reproaches to the Baſeneſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> and ſo much ſenſible pity to her dear Friend, as drew Tears from the Eyes of <hi>Pariſatis;</hi> her Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on hitherto having given it ſelf a more Manly ſort of vent, her Pride being indeed too high for ſo much weakneſs in her Eyes, as ſo Feminine a Diſtillation. But beſide the Rudeneſs and Ingratitude of <hi>Orleans,</hi> in ſo publick and audacious a Slight of a Lady ſo much more deſerving than himſelf (for ſuch her kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and eſteem of <hi>Pariſatis</hi> was pleaſed to think her) ſhe had another no leſs Hainous Accuſation againſt him, for his Wickedneſs: That his baſe vile Lendneſs ſhould dare to entertain a Thought of ſuch Impiety, as to form Deſigns againſt the Virtue of her <hi>Pariſatis.</hi> And her Reflection thereupon (ſo tender was the nice Virtue of the Queen) made her look back with Horror and Trembling, to think how often her own Ears (how Innocent or Ignorant ſoever) had been profaned with ſo many unhallowed Sounds directed to ſo wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed an end, as remembring that all his leud Addreſſes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:31510:15"/> (as gilded as they were) were made in her own Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence—To Sum up the many and long Plaints the generous Queen was pleaſed to make, in exploding the Ingratitude of the guilty Monſieur, and the Wrongs of the unfortunate <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> would be too tedious a Recital for our preſent Treatiſe. Let it ſuffice that Hours, Days and Nights were ſpent between them on that Melancholy Subject. And as low-prized as her Merit ſtood in <hi>Orleans</hi>'s lighter Ballance, her Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter and Value was not leſſened in the Eſteem of <hi>A</hi>—who continued ſtill rather the more paſſionate and faithful <hi>Statira;</hi> whilſt the Wrongs of her Friend, like the Foil to the Diamond, had only renderd her more Lovely; there being no Tenderneſs nor Endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment wanting, to ſhew ſhe was a Jewel worn next her Heart; whilſt our <hi>Pariſatis</hi> at the ſame time daily pour'd her whole Boſom forth to her Gracious Royal Miſtreſs, excepting only that ſhe cautiouſly concealed the Cardinal's and her own ſworn Revenge againſt him. For Malice is ever that <hi>Matchiavil</hi> Politician that Mines ſo low, that nothing but its own Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanthorn Light muſt peep into it. That only Secret was of Importance too weighty for the Truſt even of the Higheſt Friendſhip; for ſhe conſidered that in the intended Circle of her own and her Uncles Ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance, poſſibly there might be thoſe conjured Devils raiſed up, too frightful an Apparition for ſo tender a Conſtitution as the Queens. The Queen was ſo too much a Devote, ſo over-zealous her Principles and Practice of Religion and Piety, as would render her but an ill Confident in ſuch an Intreague; Rancor and Envy being unſociable Companious for Roſaries and Prayer-books; and therefore for the Poyſon and Gall now brewing, the Queens Breaſt was wiſely thought too nice or too weak a Chryſtal to hold them.</p>
            <p>Our Monſieur all this while under the Diſguſt of his Baniſhment from Court, was no inconſiderable Male-content. And amongſt thoſe of his Followers, that made their ſeveral Deſcants upon the Rencounter
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:31510:15"/> between himſelf and the Cardinal, there were ſome of the Boldeſt of them, who in Pity or Affection for the Young Lady, were pleaſed to argue in her Favour, and tell him, <hi>That though it muſt be acknowledged his own High Birth entituled him to a more dignified Choice than the Niece of a Prelate for a Wife for the Royal</hi> Orleans: <hi>However, as Princes have often diſpenſed with meaner Deſerts than her own; with Submiſſion to the Monſieur, they thought, that at leaſt after his former more Princely Choice of more Illuſtrious Quality, it were little or no Blemiſh in his Royal Scutcheon, to be once over-ruled more by pure Love than rigid Honour in this laſt Election: And therefore, what through the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her Alliance to the High and Potent</hi> Richlieu, <hi>her Intereſt in the Friendſhip of the Queen; but above all, the Recommendation of ſo much Youth, Wit, Beauty and Virtue; they were of opinion, that the Monſieur's Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in this caſe, had been no ſuch impardonable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcention. Virtue!</hi> (replied the Monſieur a little ſmartly) <hi>Yes; ask the He Goat her <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle Cardinal elſe, that old Phariſaick Letcher in his own Tribe. No, Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> (continued <hi>Gaſton) if I had a ſmall itching Fancy for my private Recreation, to come in as a fair Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter at a little harmleſs</hi> Level-de-coyl, <hi>I think it had been kind enough in taking the unnatural Drudgery off of his ſanctified Hands, without hanging a Church-Relique about my Neck in an Eccleſiaſtical Collar, and making a Nooſe for Life on't. No, my kind Counſellors, I durſt not play ſo bold a piece of Knight-Errantry for her, as Diſpenſing a Power as you are pleaſed to give my Honour and Me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This ill-natur'd Rallery upon his own and his Niece's Vertue, deliver'd ſo hideous in the Original, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſened or loſt in the carrying (as Malice is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways fleet of wing) ſoon reacht the Cardinals Ear; and made an impreſſion, if poſſible, deeper than the firſt affront, as heightned in ſome circumſtances above it, that being an Act more of Heat and Paſſion, but this of Study and Premeditation, But when it came
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:31510:16"/> to <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> (the Cardinal being ſtill the fatal Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) her unbridled Rage was turned into down right raving and diſtraction; to wiſh her ſelf the Eyes of a Baſilisk, the Aſpect of a <hi>Gorgon,</hi> the Treſſes of a Fury, or that with her own hand ſhe might but have the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to root his impious Heart up, were her leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>travagant expreſſions. Such an infernal Spirit of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction! Such a tremendous maſs of Forgeries againſt her unſpotted Vertue, as an execrable pollution with her own Uncle! The innocent fondneſs of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals (poſſibly) more than common Paternal Love, and her own aſſiduous Filial Duty ſo perverted! ſo blackned! ſo deformed! In fine, exaſperated and incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed into a perfect raging Libertine, ſhe flew out into the moſt vehement inveteracy againſt the Be-divel'd <hi>Orle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> that ungovern'd Female Paſſion, or Deſperation it ſelf could invent. Inſomuch that the Cardinal was forced to uſe his beſt Rhetorick to diſperſe, at leaſt, ſome part of the too outragious ſtorm, by telling her, <hi>That if his own envyed Greatneſs in the World (for he could impute it to no other cauſe) had raiſed ſo monſtrous an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halation, ſo ridiculous a Calumny againſt him, he was ſorry indeed (poor Innocence) that any part of it ſhould touch her; but at the ſame time was ſomething pleaſed at leaſt in the Incredibleneſs of the Scandal, as being too fabulous to find Reputation with any thing but the groſſeſt of Ignorance and Stupidity;</hi> in which Liſt belike Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur was one of the number.</p>
            <p>Matters thus ſtanding, we muſt now lead our Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Cardinals thoughtful Pillow, and there examin the Minerals compounding, and the Bolts a forging, for the Execution of that vow'd Vengeance, which only waits for Strength and Power worthy the Cauſe that moves it, and the Hand that weilds it, to rowl down on the Head of <hi>Orleans.</hi> In his unſleeping Meditations on that Subject, the Cardinal conſider'd the Monſieur's boundleſs Pride, founded chiefly on his ſtanding the viſible Heir of <hi>France.</hi> For as the King (as before mentioned) for above twenty tedious
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:31510:16"/> years, that long reproachful Age had now ſlept, and perhaps only ſlept in the Arms of the fair <hi>A</hi>—and <hi>Lucina</hi> not ſo much as once called in all this time. No Fruit from that fair Tree; no, not ſo much as a promiſing Bloſſom or Bud towards it; ſo little pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of an Heir of Empire from this ill matcht Pair, that even the Phyſitians themſelves in all their higheſt Court-Flattery, the common ſin of their Profeſſion, through all their Medicinal Proſpectives, had not yet ever diſcover'd even a Symptom of one, and in truth, not ſo much as a Foundation laid, or an Eſſay made towards one. Thus after the whole Court and the whole Kingdoms worn-out-Hopes of the leaſt <hi>Scion</hi> from the preſent Regal Root, the univerſal Deſpair of <hi>France</hi> had now fixt their Eyes on the Monſieur as their ſucceeding Sovereign; whilſt the Devoirs, the Veneration, and the Knees on that only account were the greateſt, if not the only Supporters of his proudeſt Greatneſs, and moſt inſulting Vanity.</p>
            <p>This Conſideration led his muſing Thought to this Queſtion with himſelf. What if yet late as it was, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gines might be ſet at work, Addreſs, Art and Eloquence managed, and natural means at laſt uſed, that the Queen might yet bear a Son from her own Body to inherit the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> and thereby totally daſh the Monſieur's aſpiring Hopes, and cruſh his whole tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering Pride at that one mortal ſhock? The very firſt ſtart upon this darling thought ſpread ſo pleaſing a Titillation through the whole Veins of the Cardinal, that he hug'd himſelf at the very conception, and look'd upon it even in the firſt Embrio as the ſublimeſt Machination of the moſt exquiſite reach of Revenge, and a Projection worth the Soul of <hi>Richlieu.</hi> Accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly his intire Study and the whole Faculties of his mind, are bent and intent upon no other Deſign. And for the promiſing Feaſibleneſs of the Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, he preſently revolves with himſelf, that the whole Default of Royal Iſſue lay only on the King's Part, and that no Deficience on the Female ſide, had
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:31510:17"/> all this while obſtructed the faireſt Happineſs of the Kingdom in an undoubted numerous Royal Progeny, that long e'er this had bleſs'd the Hopes of <hi>France,</hi> had the Abilities of the Unfortunate <hi>Lewis</hi> been but anſwerable to the Fair <hi>A</hi>—'s Merits, or his long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peoples Wiſhes. The compleat Accompliſhment therefore of ſo good and ſo great a Work, in this ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitated caſe, lyes only in the artful Introducement of ſome charitable Aſſiſtant, to ſupply the Conjugal Indigence and Wants of the poor pitied King, and borrowing abroad what cannot be found at home; a Crutch not the firſt time made uſe of, for the timely Support of a failing Family.</p>
            <p>This Propoſal, as reaſonable as it appears, has ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs this formidable Oppoſition lying in the way, <hi>viz.</hi> The Queens ſevere Virtue and inviolable Chaſtity, as almoſt (upon due Reflection) ſtaggers the whole Enterprize. He very well remembers, to his no ſmall Grief at preſent, that never was Life and Converſation more exemplary for Devotion and Piety than the Queens: A Lady whoſe conſtant Practiſe had held ſo unſhaken a Conformity to the Strictneſs of her Education, that ſhe ſtartled at the very Shadow of a Sin: A Lady ſo Famous for the many and ſingular Chriſtian Offices performed by her in the moſt conſpicuous Acts of Charity, ſome of them of that Condeſcention, even below her Imperial Dignity: Her Conſcience of that Nicety, as in all Humane Appearance muſt render her Honour altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inacceſſible. Inſomuch, that upon a ſerious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view, he meets with thoſe apparent Difficulties, which to a Soul leſs reſolved than <hi>Richlieu,</hi> would make him quit the Attempt as impracticable, and the Succeſs impoſſible.</p>
            <p>Reſolved then, as he is, he conſiders, like a true Engineer, which way the ſubtle Mine muſt work, and where the weakeſt ſide, to make the moſt advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Approach. For this he can fancy no Movement ſo cunning, as firſt guining her Confeſſor to the Party,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:31510:17"/> engaging him in the Plot, and ſo making uſe of Ghoſtly Influence, and Eccleſiaſtical Policy in the Operation. Under that Shelter what Golden Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences can he want! Neceſſity of State, the Glory of a Kingdom (and what not? as may be managed) nay, the very Safety of the King her Husband, and even the Service of Heaven it ſelf ſhall be Intereſted in her Conſent; that the very Tranſgreſſion ſweetened and ſoftned into Virtue and Piety, even Innocence ſhall Combat Innocence, and Honour Battle Honour, till Love and Pleaſure bear away the Trophy and the Triumph: The Rhetorick of a Conſcience Guide, eſpecially where Fleſh and Blood is the Argument, poſſibly carrying that perſwaſive Eloquence over im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicit Believers, that nothing like Church-Muſick to tune her into Love.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal, for moving of this Machine, preſently conſiders he has one of the beſt Tools for his purpoſe, that his own Heart could wiſh, or rather the whole Sanctified Robe could yield him, <hi>viz.</hi> Father <hi>Joſeph,</hi> a Capuchine, his own intire and abſolute Creature, and at preſent the Queens Confeſſor; one whoſe very inſide he knows ſo well, as that the undiſputed Will of his Patron the Cardinal is his guiding Oracle, and that there cannot be that Deſign of what Stamp ſoever, that (he is well aſſured) Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> will not readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and joyfully embarque in, with all Fidelity and Secrecy; and without Heſitation Scruple or Reſerve, either to ſerve his Intereſt, or gratifie his Pleaſure. The very Perſon of the World too; who beſides his being not only the propereſt Inſtrument, and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulleſt Coadjutor in this Affair, as a Man principled for ſuch a Deſign; but who alſo in his preſent Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence in the Court and Kingdom, as ſtanding fair for a Cardinals Cap (a Promotion which the ſpecial Favour of <hi>Richlieu</hi> had been ſo ſtrenuouſly endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring for him, and thereby a Chain that more firmly link'd his Heart to him) had conſequently a Power equal to his Inclinations of ſerving him. For
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:31510:18"/> this Truſty <hi>Joſeph</hi> therefore is an immediate Diſpatch ſent, and a cloſe Conference held; where the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal at large recounts his Grievances (which indeed were no Secret to <hi>Joſeph</hi> before) and after the moſt pathetick Remonſtrance of the unpardonable Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities put upon him by <hi>Orleans,</hi> together with his own reſolved Juſtice in revenging himſelf, he comes to the particular determined Means and Artifice for executing it, and thereupon deſires his kindeſt and beſt Aſſiſtance in it.</p>
            <p>Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> proud of the Glory of ſo high a Truſt, and glad of all Occaſions of teſtifying his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Bonds of Gratitude to ſo Illuſtrious a Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor, as thinking his ableſt Services at beſt but a Tributary Acknowledgment of his own ALL received and held from <hi>Richlieu,</hi> preſently aſſures him of his ſteddieſt and moſt vigorous Performance of his Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencies Sacred Commands, telling him (with a Tranſport in his very Countenance) that Fortune in all the Lottery of an Age, could never have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented ſuch an opportunity, ſo lucky an offer'd Minute for Accompliſhing ſuch a Deſign upon the Queen as now. <hi>For, Sir,</hi> continued <hi>Joſeph, to make bold to crack a Seal of Confeſſion, I muſt tell you, that the Queen at her laſt Shrift, has confeſs'd her ſelf paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately fallen in Love. And though your Eminence knows our Eccleſiaſtical Key of Conſciences unlocks almoſt all the Secrets of Courts and Kingdoms, however our Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Commiſſion in caſes of this nature, out of a tenderneſs for Perſonal Reputation, extends not to an Inquiry into Names. 'Tis enough that the Female Penitent, under more heavy Circumſtances, more mortal Dilemma's than the poor Innocent Queen, is obliged to the Penance of a Bluſh, in expoſing her ſhamefulleſt Frailty to her Confeſſors Ear, without ſpecifying the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or declaring the name of her Seducer, though the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vader of her Virgin Chaſtity, or the Violator of her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jugal Sacrament. Nevertheleſs the Queen, poor harmleſs Creature, who, God knows, I believe, had ſcarce a thought
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:31510:18"/> that ever went aſtray that way before (at leaſt I can anſwer for thoſe years ſhe has continued under my Ghoſtly Tuition) came yeſterday to Confeſſion, and with a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition as great as ſome Sinners would have felt for robbing an Altar or burning a Church, without mincing Circumſtances, or Particulars, and with an innocent open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs both of place and time, confeſs'd ſhe had unhappily caſt a look and a wandring thought (not to mention the hard names ſhe gave 'em) upon a young Stranger, that danced with her the other night at your Eminencies Ball, expreſſing in ſo mortifying an Accent, that hainous Senſe of her Tranſgreſſion in ſo guilty a Breach of her Conjugal Duty (though God wot but in a look and thought) as if ſhe had broken the whole Ten Commandments; that I dare Swear I might have enjoyn'd her the walking bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foot through the longeſt Street in</hi> Paris, <hi>and the poor thing thought it but reaſonable, had I had ſo little Chriſtianity as to have inflicted ſo cruel a Penance for ſo venial a Sin. 'Tis true, I muſt own ſhe did not utter his name (for I believe ſhe hardly knew it) however my Curioſity upon ſo novel a Confeſſion from the Queen, giving me ſome inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive Thoughtfulneſs upon ſo ſurprizing a Subject, has ſince plainly pointed out the Man to me, who muſt undoubtedly be the ſame gallant young Gentleman, an unknown Face in Court, whoſe Figure at your laſt Ball drew ſo many Eyes upon him; and whoſe Title (which I have likewiſe ſince diſcovered) is the</hi> Chevalier de Roan, <hi>a ſprightly young Gentleman of noble Extraction, who educated abroad in his tenderer Youth, has brought home the Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Gentleman and a Traveller to grace his native Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The finding of a Golden Mine could not have been half ſo welcom to the Cardinal, as this Intelligence of Father <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s, ſo infinite a Treaſure he now thought himſelf Maſter of, in ſo proſperous a Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. And looking back upon the Extraordinarineſs of paſt Circumſtances, <hi>viz.</hi> That the very Minute that <hi>Orleans</hi>'s bold Hand, and bolder Arrogance durſt ſo impudently lift it ſelf up againſt him at his own Ball,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:31510:19"/> the Queen ſhould ſo fortunately at the ſame time play the amorous Rover, twining ſo lucky a Snare about her Heart; as if the ſame over-ruling Deſtiny that ſuffered ſo loud-tongued an Affront given to his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and Honour, was in Juſtice to himſelf ſo ſtudious for the Reparation, as that at the ſame moment it permitted the Guilt, it was alſo knotting the very Whip for the Puniſhment. Reflecting I ſay in this manner, his Fancy plaid ſo much the Self-flatterer, that he could not look upon the whole Adventure as matter of Accident, the meer blind caſt of Chance; but that no leſs than the Hand of Heaven it ſelf was in it, and conſequently his intended purpoſe carried both Honour and Honeſty along with it from ſo po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent a Juſtification. But however his Cauſe did not want any of this beautiful Varniſh to ſet it off; for Revenge ſo naturally dear to the Conſtitution and Kidneys of <hi>Richlieu</hi> even in the blackeſt Face was always lovely. But to loſe no time, but lay hold of the Forelock, and fall upon Buſineſs, his immediate Determination is to ſend for the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> and to take him into his own Protection; and the firſt mark of his Favour ſhall be to introduce him into Court, and plant him in ſome honorable Office near the Perſon of the Queen, a Stand very neceſſary for the Game in hand. And for that, his own uncontroled Diſpoſal of all Honours in Court (and, in truth, in the whole Kingdom) paved his way ſo fair for him, that the Cardinal's leaſt word was a perfect Patent Royal for any Grant of that kind. And conſidering farther, that Loves beſt Arrow is Golden-headed, and the gayeſt Shaft ſtrikes deepeſt, he reſolves that if the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s private Fortunes (whatever they are) ſhall be any thing too narrow to furniſh out an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page for this Expedition, his own kind Purſe ſhall be open to ſupport that higheſt Court Grandeur as may dreſs him up the faireſt Mark for a Royal Eye: So far will he be from ſtarving ſo glorious a Cauſe, for the Crowning of whoſe Succeſs, he cannot think the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:31510:19"/> Exhauſting a whole Exchequer a profuſeneſs too Laviſh or ill Spent. And therefore the whole Reſult at this time between them is, that this Initiation of the <hi>Chevalier</hi> to the Queen; Converſation, ſhall be firſt managed, before himſelf and Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> come to a cloſer Attack of the Queen, reſerving their far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Meaſures to new Counſels, as occaſion ſhall ariſe, or neceſſity require.</p>
            <p>Means therefore is preſently uſed for bringing the <hi>Chevalier</hi> to the Cardinal's preſence, who no ſooner ſaw, and entertained him, but he deſcryed all thoſe Manly Charms both in his Perſon and Converſation, as rendred the ſhaking of the Queens Heart from ſo powerful an Aſſailant, a leſs ſubject of the Cardinal's Wonder. For though he had partly taken notice of him at the Ball, and remembred he had ſeen him Dance with the Queen; yet the Cardinal's Thoughts being then otherwiſe taken up, he had not leaſure for that Obſervation which his preſent more critical Survey of ſo deſerving an Object affords him. The Cardinal, whoſe penetrating Judgment poſſibly could read a Man through at as quick a ſight as any Perſon of the Age, received that inſtant Satisfaction, and that enlightening of his hopes from an Aſpect ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing, as carried him to the moſt vigorous puſhing on of the preſent ſmiling Fortune before him. After ſeveral Queſtions relating to his Birth, Education and Travels (the chief Subject of the preſent Interview) to all which, the <hi>Chevalier</hi> anſwered with that grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Aſſurance, in an account ſo pertinently delivered, and likewiſe with all that Sweetneſs, as added a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Illuſtration to that Worth which each Minute appeared but more conſpicuous: The Cardinal, in return, addreſſing to the <hi>Chevalier,</hi> told him, <hi>That as the Advancement of Virtue and Merit had been always his Study, he had received that Character of him, which ſupported by ſo many fair Credentials now before him had recommended him to his Favour; and therefore he required his attendance to morrow Morning to receive ſome
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:31510:20"/> Pledge of it, and in the mean time to be aſſured that his Fortune ſhould be his own Dependant.</hi> The tranſported <hi>Chevalier,</hi> who deſired no greater good Fortune than Court-Smiles could build him, and no greater a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of ſuch a Fortune than <hi>Richlieu;</hi> Power, Honor or Truſt in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> being really the Work of no other Creation than his own; made the Cardinal a return of that moſt ſenſible Duty for ſo dazling a Grace as his Eminence in this ſurprizing manner was pleaſed ſhould ſhine down upon him, taking his leave with that profound Obeyſance, that he carried home with him ſuch pleaſing Idea's from ſo elevating a Meditation, as ſweetned his whole Thoughts all day, and gilded his very Dreams all night.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal has no ſooner diſpatch'd the <hi>Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier,</hi> but ſtrait he poſts to the Queen, where the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Viſit was to tell her Majeſty, <hi>That he came a Suitor to her in the behalf of Merit. Merit, my Lord,</hi> anſwered the Queen, <hi>and ſuch an Interceſſor for it, are very prevailing Orators in any reaſonable Suit. The Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonableneſs of my Suit,</hi> replied the Cardinal, <hi>I'll refer to your fair Self, when telling you I have occaſions of State to remove an Officer now in Service under your Majeſty to another poſt, I would intreat your gracious Acceptance of a ſupply to fill his vacancy in the Perſon of a Gentleman, who beſides noble Friends, has nobler Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues his Advocates. 'Tis true, he is ſomething a Stranger in Court, and I ſuppoſe unknown to your Majeſty, though I confeſs your Majeſty has ſeen him once at leaſt; and if amongſt your numerous Denations of the like Favour at that time, your Majeſty might chance to take notice of him, I could recall him to your remembrance by reminding you, that your Majeſty did him the Honour to Dance with him at the Ball the other night: And though as young a Courtier as he is, yet being a Perſon of that remarkable Appearance, that not only the Approbation of the Court in that fair Aſſembly gave him ſome Reſpect, but my own Teſtimonials of his compleat Worth can more fully anſwer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:31510:20"/> for him, I am emboldened to preſent him to you as one of your Menials in the Capacity of your Majeſties Knight of Honour your Gentleman <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At the Cardinal's firſt mention of the Stranger that Danced with her, the Queen in ſpight of her beſt Endeavours to bide it, could not hinder the riſing of a little extraordinary Vermilion in her Cheeks, which the Cardinal with a Secret Delight perceiving, nevertheleſs in tenderneſs to the bluſhing Queen, he as induſtriouſly managed his Looks to take no notice of it, as the Queen could do her own for giving him no occaſion for it. And by that time the Cardinal had finiſh'd his Addreſs, the Queen, with much ado, had pretty well recovered her natural Complexion, and ſuppreſs'd the guilty Bloom, the lawleſs Rebel Bluſh that had made ſo bold an Invaſion ſo much againſt her Will; and at firſt Thought, out of a Secret Check of Honour, and a Religious Guard of her Virtue, ſhe had almoſt reſolved to have denied the Cardinal her Acceptance of ſo dangerous a Servant; only upon a ſudden Recollection ſhe was not provided with any reaſonable Objection againſt him, for her juſt Refuſal of ſo qualified a Perſon, unleſs ſhe would plainly, or at leaſt tacitly have confeſs'd the true cauſe of her Denial, and thereby have diſcovered her guilty Weakneſs to the Cardinal, a Frailty ſo ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, as ſhe could ſooner paſs an Ordeal, than but once think of expoſing. Enforced therefore to a conſent, ſhe made the Cardinal a ſhort Anſwer, telling him, <hi>He needed not to have given himſelf all this Trouble, but have uſed his own pleaſure; for the Choice of her Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants being always the leaſt of her care, he beſt knew who were the Perſons fitteſt for her.</hi> And ſo with an affected Indifference, and by way of Prevention to all Danger of any new Inſurrection of a ſecond Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Bluſh, ſhe diverted the Subject by falling into Diſcourſe of other Matters, with no little pleaſure to her ſelf at ſo prudent a conduct herein, though Heaven knows to a quite contrary Effect; for little
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:31510:21"/> thinking what Hands, Poor Lady, ſhe is now fallen into, the Artfulneſs of her affected Innocence, is only a plainer Indication of what ſhe moſt labours to conceal.</p>
            <p>The next Morning at the appointed hour of Atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance, the <hi>Chevalier</hi> waits the Cardinal's Upriſing, when the generous <hi>Richlieu</hi> taking him alone with him into his Cloſet, he told him, <hi>As an Earneſt of his Favour, and an Introduction to his future good Fortune, he deſign'd to place him near the Perſon of the Queen, in the Quality and Poſt of Her Majeſties Gentleman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher. And that he might make his Entrance not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy himſelf, he deſired his Acceptance of thirty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crowns for ſome little preſent help:</hi> Giving him far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to underſtand that his pleaſure was, <hi>That no Perſon ſhould appear in more Splendor at Court than himſelf:</hi> And to encourage him to be no ways ſparing in any Equipage neceſſary thereunto, <hi>He aſſured him his own Hand ſhould never be ſhut to him, but a conſtant Aſſiſtance ſhould daily flow from the ſame kind Fountain to ſupport that Figure he intended he ſhould make; only one Injunction he muſt lay upon him, which was, that, as his Favours were never ſullied with the Affectation of Vanity; for that reaſon, and ſome other private ones of his own, he conjured him to make at leaſt this part of his Kindneſs an inviolable Secret.</hi> The <hi>Chevalier</hi> utterly confounded (as well he might) at ſo pouring a Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of Bounty, fell inſtantly upon his Knees to thank his generous Patron, in a Language and Poſture ſuit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Reception of ſuch accumulated Graces in ſo aſtoniſhing a manner heap'd upon him. For as the Seaſon was not yet thought ripe to unſeal the <hi>Chevalier</hi>'s Commiſſion in the Poſt to which he was entring, the Cardinal's Favours appeared ſo much the more magnified, as that the <hi>Chevalier</hi> was at preſent wholly ignorant, that there was concealed Vengeance as well as open Love in ſo extravagant a Benefactor, and that a deſcending Thunderer lay hid in the Golden Shower. The Cardinal was pleaſed likewiſe
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:31510:21"/> to queſtion the Chevalier, if he were married or no; to which the Chevalier modeſtly anſwering in the Negative, the Cardinal told him, <hi>That as he had made him his own Adoption, his whole Preferment ſhould be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely his own Care;</hi> and therefore he enjoyned him not to engage himſelf in any Amour without his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacy; for with the Diſpoſal of himſelf, the Diſpoſal of his Heart too he intended ſhould be his own par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Care.</p>
            <p>The Chevalier, whoſe natural Ambition and Vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty (to give him his right) perhaps the World could hardly match, in perſuance of the Cardinals Will and Pleaſure, the extraordinary Splendor and Gallantry order'd him to appear in, reſolved rather to out-do, than fall ſhort in his Obedience to that part of his Command. For not only the Cardinal's Bounty (ſhower as often and as much as it kindly pleaſe) but his whole Patrimony, rather than want, ſhould be all ventured on the ſame Bottom.</p>
            <p>Our gay Chevalier thus pompouſly enſtated, has not ſhin'd many days in his Office, before the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal thinks fit to ſend for him, to cloſet him once more, and there open the great <hi>Arcanum</hi> to him, with all the neceſſary Documents for the Conduct and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age of it. After ſeveral other Careſſes, the Cardinal for feeling his Pulſe, asks the Chevalier his Opinion of the Queen, and how he likes his Royal Miſtriſs. To which the Chevalier, <hi>Like her! and pleaſe your Eminence! 'tis impoſſible but every thing that is humane muſt kneel to ſuch Divine Goodneſs; nay, her very mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring Angels, her Guardians themſelves, muſt certainly be in Love with her. Nay, my Chevalier,</hi> reply'd the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, <hi>now you ſpeak like a paſſimate Servant indeed: But I perceive you are rightly qualified for a Courtier, you can play the Flatterer ſo expertly. No, my Lord,</hi> reply'd the Chevalier, <hi>Whatever other Qualifications of a Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er I may juſtly mourn the want of, I am no ways deſirous of that common Court-trapping, Flattery, as faſhionable as 'tis now worn. Beſides, I believe, your Eminence is ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:31510:22"/> of that Royal Merit in the Perſon of the Queen that deſerves a better and abler Panegyriſt than my ſelf; the higheſt Character I can give ſuch ſublime Excellency, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing only the univerſal Duty of all that have the Honour to be bleſt with the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>mbrage of it, and that I am no more than one of the Croud that pay it her. Well, my Chevalier,</hi> anſwered the Cardinal, ſmiling, <hi>the Queen is not ungrate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for the kind Character you give her, for ſhe is pleaſed to return the Chevalier as a kind one. But to put one Question to you; Could you love the Queen? Love her! my Lord!</hi> anſwered the Chevalier ſomething ſurpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed. <hi>Yes,</hi> ſays the Cardinal, <hi>Love her! Love that Divine Goodneſs you have painted ſo beautiful. Examin your Heart, and faithfully anſwer me that ſerious Queſtion. My Lord,</hi> anſwered the Chevalier, <hi>there's ſomething ſo amazing in the Queſtion demanded, that I am unprovided with ſenſe enough to underſtand you: But ſince your Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence's abſolute Command repaires my Anſwer, and I dare not be ſo inſolent to ask an explication, I can only reply, That had Providence, the great Diſpoſer, debaſed the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of the fair</hi> A—<hi>level to the poor Chevalier</hi> de Roan, <hi>or advanced mine up to hers; and the Divine Diſpenſer ſo ordain'd to lodge ſuch Beauty in my Arms, I could out-pride my ſelf in ſuch a Prize above the famous</hi> Alexander <hi>with his conquered <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe, Lord of a fairer World than his Sword ever conquered, or his Ambition wept for.</hi> The Cardinal rouch'd with a pleaſure to find the Wax ſo ſoft and ſo fair for the Impreſſion, began at large to unfold from the whole beginning (without the leaſt conceal'd particular) the Queens favour for the Chevalier; and in fine, the whole Structure to be rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed on that Baſis. Only he a little minced the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate revenge engaged in it, and laid the more weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſtreſs on that more popular Argument, the ſafety and the glory of the Nation ſo zealouſly labour'd for, in raiſing an Heir from the Body of the Queen; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding the charming Subject (for ſuch the raviſh'd Soul of the Chevalier began to feel it) with this clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing point, <hi>Well, my Chevalier, if the Royal Grace of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:31510:22"/> the Queen, and the Intereſt of your aſſiſting Friends are planting ſo fair a Grove of Lawrels for you in the ſtoln pleaſure of ſo ſweet a Paradice, I hope you are not of too ſtrait-ſaced a Conſcience, but ſo fair a Lady—Conſcience, my Lord!</hi> (replied the Chevalier, interrupting him) <hi>No; there's that higher Divinity in the fair</hi> A—<hi>'s Charms, that truckling Conſcience moves a Sphear below it. The en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyment of ſuch Bliſs carries its own Conſecration; and I could mix my Oriſons to ſuch Beauty, even with my Prayers to Heaven.</hi> This amorous Rapture of the Chevalier's had a little tang of Profaneneſs in it, being ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of a bold Launch before ſo high a Church-pillar; however the Cardinal's Sanctity reliſh'd it never the worſe on this occaſion; and finding ſo hopeful a Knight-Errant of him for marching under a Lady's Banner, he told him what obſtacles lay in the way, in the rigid Vertue and Chaſtity they had to combat. However, not to let that diſhearten him, the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounting of thoſe Bars for him, ſhall be his own and Father <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Work. For as thick a maſs of Ice as Honour had hardned about her Heart, they had In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe and Altar Coles ready to thaw it; and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion it ſelf ſhould be the miniſtring Inſtrument made uſe of for ſoftning her moſt obdurate Scruples of Conſcience. And therefore the Chevalier's buſineſs was only to be very aſſiduous and officious about the Perſon of the Queen, his ſilent Services being all the Addreſs he muſt dare to make; for the diſtance of a Crown'd Head would admit of no bolder an approach, his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince being no more than to attend the conſummation of his deſtined Felicity; and waiting for the golden Fruit, till they had ripen'd it for gathering. But above all things he was to remember, (and that with a moſt religious obſervance) that he was puſhing for that Conqueſt which would admit of no Triumph. For there was more than Fairy Treaſure in the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing deſigned him; a Secret to be ſealed up in eternal ſilence, and prized as valuable as his Life.</p>
            <p>This private Conference of the Chevalier and the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:31510:23"/> Cardinal was now interrupted by a Viſit of his Niece's; and the Chevalier diſmiſs'd with that entire ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thoſe Raptures about him, that he could ſcarcely think he trod on common Ground, but look'd upon himſelf as already tranſlated to ſome more than humane <hi>Elyſium,</hi> from the Aſpect of ſo many gaudy Viſions that now danced before him. Our <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> who being hitherto not called to the Conſult, and thereby ignorant of the great Work of Projection, and the preſent forwardneſs of it, thought the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal's Bolts a little ſlow a forging; and in truth was making this Viſit for lending her help to the Bellows, or (rather than fail) to the Hammer to haſten them. But Fortune at this time ſpares her the needleſs trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; for the Cardinal prevents her the Queſtion, by voluntarily making her the Partner of his own Joys, in a Relation at large, containing the whole Progreſs of their Plot, and the full proſpect of their Succeſs. Our <hi>Pariſatis</hi> lent an Ear to the Narration with as much Attention as to a deliver'd Oracle; and though it plainly terminated in down-right betraying the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and rifling the Chaſtity of her deareſt and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt <hi>Statira;</hi> yet whether all the moſt ſacred and bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ties of Friendſhip were ſwallowed in the inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate and undiſtinguiſhing Thirſt of Vengeance; or that perhaps her Feminine Pity to the Queen for her twenty long abſtinential years, might think a Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plot no unfriendly deſign againſt her, ſhe could not forbear giving the Cardinal the higheſt Applauſe, as due for this Maſterpiece of Invention. The Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal finding his Niece's Pulſe beat ſo even with his own, was pleaſed to tell her, that her Faculties too muſt be exerciſed, as well as Father <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s and his own, <hi>viz.</hi> in ſeeking all occaſions before the Queen, of extolling the Wit, Perſon and Gallantry of the Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier; there being no whet to Love like Praiſe, nor can the Queens Fancy be better edged. <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> whoſe too zealous revenge againſt <hi>Orleans</hi> was aſhamed to ſtand an idle Spectator in a Cauſe ſo much her own,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:31510:23"/> readily aſſented to joyn in the Triple League, and heartily make one amonſt them, promiſing her ableſt helping Hand for the turning of any Wheel in her power to ſetting of the great Machine a moving.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pariſatis</hi> was not admitted into the Conſult in vain: for there was ſcarce a day paſs'd that ſhe did not art<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully inſinuate into the Queen a good Thought, and a kind Eye for the Chevalier. If the Chevalier had any Acceſs more than ordinary to the Queen, 'twas through <hi>Pariſatis.</hi> His Services and Aſſiduity were magnified with all the little Arts of her beſt Manage and Applauſe. Nor only this, but ſhe cunningly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged him in thoſe pleaſing Narrations before the Queen of his Travels, Obſervations, and Adventures in <hi>Italy, Germany,</hi> and ſeveral other parts of the World, as infinitely contributed to the Queens Divert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſement; and which ſo ingeniouſly related, diſcovered a Treaſury of that rich Wit and Senſe in the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh'd Chevalîer, as could not but plume new Darts from this new Quiver, and heighten the impending Fatality of thoſe more and more dangerous Charms, which were before but too mortal.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal in the mean while conſidering how re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite it would be for himſelf to act in conjunction with Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> in the Religious Attack upon the Queen, the great Church-battery to be planted againſt her; not doubting his own Ability in furniſhing a great many ſinewy and forcible Arguments, the neceſſary Artillery towards it; and yet on the other ſide re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting on his own known Rancour and Revenge againſt <hi>Orleans,</hi> he finds himſelf a very unqualified Orator on that Theme. For in ſpight of all the pretended fair Face of Zeal and Religion deſigned for their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, he is but too ſenſible that the Queens piercing Judgment will diſcover the Vizer, and detect the rooted and gangreen'd malice at the bottom. But for wiſe prevention of all this, he inſtantly reſolves upon this Expedient, <hi>viz.</hi> by Father <hi>Joſeph</hi> and other private A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, to have the Monſieur recalled to Court, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:31510:24"/> to appear ſo cool, ſo eaſie, and indeed ſo gall-leſs in the remiſſion of ſo heinous an Affront, as ſhall ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſtifle all ſuſpicion of the leaſt remaining Dreg of Spight or Reſentment againſt him. Accordingly the next News we hear, is the Return of the Monſieur. His Baniſhment ſo gently repeal'd without either Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ask'd, or the leaſt Atonement or Submiſſion made; that the huſhing up of ſo noiſie a Storm in ſo ſudden and unexpected a Calm, is the Subject of univerſal wonder; inſomuch that the whole Conduct of the tame-forgiving Cardinal herein, much to their aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, appeared more agreeable to the meekneſs of a cloiſtered Saint, than the Spirit of a State Church-man; and ſo publickly reſounded his more than Chriſtian Moderation and Lenity, as his Revenge could not well have its Cloven Foot better covered.</p>
            <p>All things carried on thus plauſibly, the indefatiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Engineer <hi>Pariſatis</hi> has ſo often gain'd the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier thoſe near and familiar Acceſſes to the Queen, that new Fewel is added to the old Fire; and the poor Quen comes big with a ſad and lamentable Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her Female Weakneſs to her Confeſſor. Her Confeſſion makes a Relation of that diſmal Violence committed upon her Heart, by the more and more prevailing Influence of her bold and formidable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croacher, as requires no ſmall expiatiory Contrition. Our well-pleaſed <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who (had it been yet time to ſpeak) would have told her, it had been more her Vertue than her Sin; however takes a very gentle cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizance of her Frailty, and gives her ſo eaſie an Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, that by the cheapneſs of her preſent Balm in <hi>Gilead,</hi> the Queen had good reaſon to believe, that her Offence (if his Ghoſtly Spectacles ſaw true) was not altogether ſo frightful as her own over-prying Terrors of Conſcience had preſented it.</p>
            <p>The Capuchin immediately poſts to the Cardinal, and gives him at large the whole pain of the Queen, and the full Dimenſions of her opening Wound, her whole Confeſſion having diſcloſed that radicated and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:31510:24"/> invincible Paſſion for the Chevalier, that to loſe no time, they think the Iron full hot for ſtriking; and if if ſhe be ever malleable, 'tis now. 'Tis reſolved therefore that the Cardinal and his truſty <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhall preſently deſire a private Audience of the Queen, and prepare for a general Storm.</p>
            <p>Such a private Conference by Perſons ſo high in her eſteem, is no ſooner ask'd but obtain'd: where the Cardinal, with a Gravity ſuitable to the occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, very eloquently, (by way of Introduction) makes a long Harangue upon the Happineſs of thoſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, where the Smiles of Providence have bleſt the Royal Bed with Heirs to Empire; recounting ſeveral Inſtances from Hiſtory in divers parts of the World of the eſtabliſhment of the Peace and Glory of Nations, founded and ſecured upon that only Baſis of their Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licity; hinting ſeveral unfortunate examples of Crowns devolving upon Collateral Lines, and the publick Feuds and fatal Troubles ariſing from that unhappy Cauſe. From this Topick he begins very artfully to condole the like unhappineſs of <hi>Lewis</hi> in Defect of Iſſue from the Illuſtrious <hi>A</hi>—'s Veins; inſinuating al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the like impending misfortune of <hi>France</hi> from that National Calamity, the preſent Childleſs Bed of <hi>Lewis;</hi> telling her how much the whole Kingdom groaned under that Affliction, and what inexpreſſible Delight and Tranſport they would receive, if Heaven even yet would hear the Prayers of an Age, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Diſtreſſes of a People, in opening that Gate to their Bliſs (as late as it was, and as long ſhut as it had been) by raiſing them a Branch from ſo Divine and ſo dear a Sovereign Stock. The Queen, who yet fathom'd not their Depth, was pleaſed modeſtly to reply, <hi>That ſhe was highly obliged both to his and her Peoples kind wiſhes. But as the immutable Will had otherwiſe ordained, they muſt all acquieſce in the Divine Pleaſure, and ceaſe thoſe fruitleſs Prayers, which Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven had now too manifeſtly decreed ſhould be in vain. Decreed, Madam!</hi> replyed the Capuchin very paſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onately,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:31510:25"/> 
               <hi>Kind Heaven forbid! No, Madam, if the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine A—a would look down with an Eye of Mercy upon a mourning Kingdom, we have no reaſon to diſtruſt but Providence would pity where you pityed. And ſince the Almighty Diſpenſation, as high and as great a Firſt-mover as it is, has not ſo wholly aſſum'd the entire care of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind to it ſelf, but in a high meaſure has remitted the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of ſome Bleſſings to inferiour and ſecond-moving Cauſes: And though our Worldly Felicities are truly all formed for us above; however there muſt be that humane co-operating Study and Induſtry, the effective Means of receiving them. And ſince (as we have too long and too juſt Reaſon with anguiſh of Soul, and fulneſs of ſorrow to lament) we your neareſt and faithfulleſt Servants are but too ſenſible of a drooping Kingdoms Loſs, and the true and only defective cauſe of their long Infelicity; my Lord Cardinal, that zealous and pious good Man, and learned Prelate, with my unworthy ſelf, are ſent to you, commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion'd from the Divine Authority, to open your Ears to the Cries of a Nation; and in the everlaſting Name, to ſoften your Compaſſion into that Maternal Care of</hi> France, <hi>as may raiſe up her languiſhing Head, and eſtabliſh her Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, Tranquility and Honour to endleſs Generations. Yes, Royal Madam,</hi> proceeded the Cardinal, <hi>With that Divine Authority, and for that great purpoſe we are come your Suppliants, beſeeching your Attention to thoſe cordial and faithful Admonitions, which, as Ambaſſadors of Truth, we are emboldned to lay down before you, under the War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant and Credentials of that Heavenly Command that ſends us. Ah, Madam, if the languiſhing</hi> Flower-de-Liſſes, <hi>a wailing Kingdoms Tears, and an Empires wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Glory could move you to Commiſeration, propitious Heaven might yet raiſe that bleſt Fruit from theſe Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Veins, as one day ſhall adorn the</hi> Gallick Throne; <hi>an Heir that my Prophetick Soul foretels ſhall Reign a Hero upon Earth, and ſhine a Saint in Heaven. But oh! the miſery! the incomprehenſible miſery that the Royal Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel in the unhappy</hi> Lewis <hi>ſhould be ſo totally block'd up, that our kneeling Vows muſt look up to ſome new Sourſe of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:31510:25"/> for ſo Divine a Bleſſing. Conſider, Gracious Lady, how the natural Orb of Glory is totally ſhaded; and let your pitying Goodneſs ſupply ſome borrowed Luminary, or all the Light of</hi> France <hi>muſt ſet for ever. Nor let any ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Fantom, (for 'tis only Fantom) from this ſhocking ſound aſſame a ſhape to fright you. For I aſſure you I come a Miniſter of Light, and not an Imp of Darkneſs; and bear a ſhining Lamp of Heaven, and not a ſooty Brand of Hell before you. No, Madam, to anſwer even to your moſt ghaſtly Fears, and diſpel the Gorgon; for I cannot make too plain a Scrutiny into ſo nice a point of Conſcience: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, Madam, that the terribleſt of Sins</hi> Adultry, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Command within the ſecond Table of the Law, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo far a Violation of the Divine Ordinance, as it is a Breach of our Duty, or a wrong to our Neighbour. The true Adultreſs is the Defiler of her Nuptial Bed in the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of her Husbands Right. But, alas, that horrid Blemiſh will no ways touch the Innocence of</hi> A—a: <hi>For a Right cannot be invaded, before a Right poſſeſs'd. As hallowed as the Matrimonial Bond, and as inviolable as the Conjugal Bed ſhould be; it is not the Sacred Words alone before the Altar that tie that Bond, and make that Conjugal Knot ſo uninfringible, but the ſtronger</hi> conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Seal <hi>of Matrimony. If any perſonal Defect renders that Conſummation impoſſible, (and indeed Marriage it ſelf under any ſuch perſonal known defect, is rather a Privarication with God, than an Holy Sacrament) the Matrimonial Obligation is of it ſelf ſo invalid, that the Law lies open to null it with a Breath, and every days common Proceſs can diſſolve it. I confeſs, could any Vows, Oblations, Prayers or Sacrifices prevail to obtain this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Bliſs to the up-raiſing a deſpairing Kingdom by an Heir from</hi> Lewis; <hi>my Soul would tremble at ſo unhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed a Motion, as this then would be, and ſink my bluſhing Face in duſt at the horror of ſo tremendous an Imagination. But ſince the fatal Wants of the lamented</hi> Lewis <hi>have barricadoed even the leaſt Glimps of Light out, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded all our Hopes from thence; what Injury, what In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:31510:26"/> to</hi> Lewis <hi>can the Fair</hi> A—a <hi>commit? What private Violation of her Shackles and Fetters (for ſuch rather than her Hymeneal Tyes I muſt call 'em) can ſhe make; eſpecially under ſo urgent a call: when even thoſe Shackles ſhe may publickly in the Face of the World, by the Laws of God and Man, utterly unbind, cancel and throw off; if fooliſh worldly Honour, that by long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing Cuſtom has laid a popular Stain on ſuch a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding, would permit ſo reproachful though ſo highly legal a Separation? Beſides, Madam, were there a ſhadow of a Fault, or any remaining unſatisfied Scruple againſt the Sacred Counſel I have given you; conſider, that when Extraordinary Occaſions call, Heaven has permitted the uſe of Extraordinary Inſtruments; and ſo warrantable have thoſe Extraordinary Inſtruments been, that the Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf has laid down Patterns and Precedents even of its own exemplar Conduct under the ſame Diſpenſation. Look back, Madam, but to the Creation of the World, and you will ſee the firſt Original of Mankind raiſed even by inceſtuous Beds, a Generation betwixt Brother and Siſter. And though at the ſame time we muſt own that the unlimited Almighty Power (had the inſcrutable Wiſdom ſo thought fit) could have otherwiſe Peopled the World; yet ſuch was his Decree, that even that which his firſt delivered Law proſcribed, and condemned as ſo black and deformed, was nevertheleſs by Himſelf under his own diſpencing Pleaſure (for Neceſſity with Omnipotence is incompatible) made the very corner Stone to that fair Fabrick, the Race of Men, the Image of Himſelf. And if, Madam, ſo univerſal a diſpencing Power was exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed for the Benefit of Mankind; ſhall one ſingular Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tencing Act for the Benefit of a whole Nation be Capital: eſpecially where that Diſpenſation infringes no Law, Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates no Right, and breaks no Command, as has ſo fully been proved to your Majeſty? Alas! Madam, 'tis the Intention makes the Sin; the Gratification of a Luſt may be Criminal, whilſt the Preſervation of a Kingdom ſhall be righteous and unblameable. But perhaps, Madam, you may have ſome little Tenderneſs to the Pretenſions of the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:31510:26"/> preſent Expectant Heirs of</hi> France, <hi>and nicely think the Diverting of Succeſſion a Treſpaſs upon their Birthright. No, Royal Madam, ſtagger not your Royal Reaſon there. Examine but the Conduct and Practice of Imperial Policy in imumerable Examples. How many of the Great Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Ceſars <hi>have Adopted Sons to Inherit, I may ſay, even the Empire of the World</hi> (for ſuch was then the Roman Greatneſs) <hi>And if Adopted Heirs, utter Aliens and Strangers to the Blood, were ſo publickly let in to riſe up in Bar of all the neareſt Imperial Demandants, and ſo notorious an Excluſion of Lineal Right juſtified by thoſe strict and critical Obſervers of Meral Juſtice the Roman Adminiſtrators; how much more Righteous will an Adoption to the Crown of</hi> France <hi>appear, when ſo far from an Alien, it ſhall challenge at leaſt</hi> half <hi>the Royal Title, the Rich Veins of the fair Partner of the Throne, the Sacred</hi> A—a; <hi>And the other Additional borrowed part, only a charitable Supply of Indigence, and ſupport of Weakneſs. Alas! Madam, (cryed the interpoſing</hi> Joſeph) <hi>let me do the noble Cardinal this right, as to avow, that not a prophecying Martyr could have delivered more oraculous Truths, than the Profound and Divine Reaſon he has uttered. Yes, Madam,</hi> replied the Cardinal, <hi>what I have uttered has been delivered in the Spirit of Truth and Fidelity, without a Taint or Sully of the leaſt malicious or ſiniſter Thought. I confeſs, indeed, I have received Wrongs from</hi> Orleans, <hi>and perhaps crying ones; But ſo forgive me Heaven, as I have forgiven him: and that I ſpeak the Sincerity of my Soul, the Eternal Witneſs can bear Record for me. Forgiven him!</hi> anſwered <hi>Joſeph</hi> very paſſionately, <hi>Yes, and ſo exemplar a Forgiveneſs, as the admiring World reſounds it even to your Reproach. That meek forgiving Goodneſs to that great bad Man, ſo much above a Chriſtian Love, and Fraternal Amity, even to a Humane Weakneſs. Believe me, Royal Madam,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the Cardinal, <hi>I have given you Counſel, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps may have ſurprized you in it; but to anſwer before the everlaſting Tribunal, for the Integrity of my Thoughts to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sacred Majeſty of</hi> France, <hi>in the Perſon of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:31510:27"/> Royal</hi> Anne <hi>of</hi> A—a, <hi>the Righteous Judge that knows the hidden Secrets, knows, that your Guardian Angel cannot bear his Charge over you more Faithfully, and would more tenderly guide your leaſt unerring Step than</hi> Richlieu. <hi>Better a Thouſand ſinking Kingdoms Mourn, than the fair Soul of</hi> A—a <hi>ſhould but trip even in a Criminal Thought, by the miſleading Counſels of</hi> Richlieu. <hi>Betray my Royal Miſtris! No! far be that abhorred deteſted Thought. And though in this weak Vale of Mortality, each Minute has its Faults and Frailties to account for; I would not have ſo black a Sin to anſwer at my laſt Audit of Eternity, as the betraying of my Royal Miſtris, for twice that Kingdoms Price, for whoſe Glory I am ſo Solicitous. No, Madam, I have given you honeſt and faithful Counſel; and to conjure you to embrace it, my Souls Eternity anſwer for yours.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Queen who all this while had never interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one ſyllable, but reſolved (patiently I dare not ſay) to give a full run to theſe aſſailing Church. Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, could now hold no longer, but falling into the moſt pathetical Exclamation, ſhe cryed, <hi>Good God! where ſhall I hide my bluſhing Head, and how ſhall I be able to look Day in the Face, to think that two ſuch Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Profeſſors of Chriſtianity durſt ask me ſuch a Queſtion? No, my Lord Cardinal, I will not enter into Diſpute with you, nor quarrel your Religious Jargon up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this ſtrange amazing Theme; for I am too weak to play the Caſtiiſt againſt ſuch Learning. But to anſwer you in my own Province; had you been a ſenſible Judge of that Worldly Honour you mentioned, you would have ſooner bit that Tongue out than have dared but motion ſuch profaration to</hi> A—a. The Cardinal was going to reply, when the Queen interrupted him, <hi>For ſhame, for ſhame, no more. Flatter me not, miſtaken Guides, with an eaſie forgiving God, to what I could ne're for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give my ſelf, and ceaſe this fruitleſs ſuit; for when you can move the Globe, hope to ſhake Me: for the Attempt is equally impoſſible.</hi> The Cardinal and the Capuchine were endeavouring to ſpeak again; when the Queen
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:31510:27"/> abſolutely commanded their ſilenſe, and with an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity in her very Look, an Aſpect that the ſweetneſs of her Temper was never ruffled into before, <hi>Bid them eternally forbear the Ropetition of this days Folly, or ſee her Face no more;</hi> and ſo bolted from them out of the Cloſet, as if ſhe meant to tell them that ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained even to converſe upon ſo loathed a Subject, and would not bear the very Air 'twas breath'd in.</p>
            <p>The Cardinal and Capuchin very mournfully with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw, and could not forbear, between themſelves, a great many hard words upon the Queens incorrigible obſtinacy and perverſeneſs. But as ſhamefully defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as they have been, however 'tis reſolved they'll ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly again; only that new Mines and Trenches muſt be managed to carry on the Approach. The Capuchine he adviſes, <hi>That ſome Love-potion or amorous Philter ſhould be given her, and in the height of the operation the Chevalier boldly looſed upon her; and that Engine could never fail ſucceſs.</hi> But the Cardinal utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liked this project, giving theſe Objections, <hi>viz. That if there were any ſuch Arts to be practis'd, their Effects were only to be wrought by Poyſon; and undoubtedly the Queens overheat, under any ſuch unnatural Ferment, would be as prejudicial as her Husbands over coldneſs had been before; and ſo their whole Deſign fall to the Ground. No, he had not Read all Divinity, but he thank'd God he was a little piece of a Naturaliſt too; and very well knew that the Current of Generation muſt keep the eaſie channel of Nature; for in all forced Torrents and violent Rapidities, the Inundation would be deſtructive. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides all ſuch Arts at beſt would lay but a crazy Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; for compulſive Love would quickly turn into Hate and Averſion; and the Charm diſſolving and ſtupyfied Reaſon awaking, a work ſo ill begun would be in danger of tottering before any perfection accompliſht.</hi> Then replies the Capuchine, <hi>What think you, Sir, if the Queen by ſome ſtratagem or other, at ſome unguarded Minute, ſhould be ſnared into the Chevaliers Arms? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider poor liarmloſs Creature, a meer Virgen as ſhe is; ſhe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:31510:28"/> is inſenſible of the unexperienced Felicity, and her Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance is the only Rock againſt us. But oh you cannot imagine, upon ſuch a ſurprize, how preſently her Ice would melt before him; the offender with his ſhort lived Guilt would quickly play that ample Peacemaker, that after the Reliſh of ſuch a riotous Feaſt of ſweets, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly the Taſt wou'd ſoon create the Appetite; and I aſſure you you need not doubt fixing him the intire Lord of her Aſcendant, and expecting a proſperous Revolution of your utmoſt Deſigns.</hi> The Cardinal intirely pleaſed could not but applaud the Capuchines depth of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and Confidence in a matter ſo extraordinary, ſo profound a humane reach being ſo much more wondrous as from a Cloyſterer, and a vow'd Recluſe; aſſuring him, <hi>He likes it ſo well, that he will ſteer to the Golden Coaſt of all his Hopes by no other Chart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Our <hi>Pariſatis</hi> (for our Hiſtory muſt now take a ſmall walk with her) who has now an Extraordinary piece of Work cut out, one Morning finds the Queen alone; and with a melancholy Look, and a deep Sigh, ſhe accoſts her in theſe few ſad Accents, <hi>Ah Madam, I am the unhappieſt of my Sex! How my</hi> Pariſatis, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Queen, <hi>what new Cloud dares ſhade that Brow? Has Fortune any more invenomed ſhafts againſt that envyed Beauty, after ſo many extravagant Bolts of her Malice in the Inſolencies of the ungrateful</hi> Orleans? <hi>Yes, Madam,</hi> (replied <hi>Pariſatis) ſhe has new Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and the ſame</hi> Orleans <hi>to pour it down upon me. For after all my Load of Injuries from that Vile Man, to compleat his Villanies, he has this Morning bribed one of my Women, this night when I am in Bed to admit him into my Chamber.</hi> The Queen was almoſt thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruck at this Relation, and replied, <hi>How, my</hi> Pariſatis, <hi>after all his impious Barbarities, has he a new Reſerve of Execrations? Is his Mine of miſchief inexhauſtible? But above all after ſo wondrous a condeſcending Mercy of the forgiving Cardinal, is this his kind Return? Yes Madam</hi> [cryed <hi>Pariſatis] to ſo generous, I might ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay, ſhameful a Remiſſion of ſo many notorious Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:31510:28"/> this is his Gratitude.</hi> The Queen was ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly alarm'd at ſo amazing a Diſcovery, and expreſt her concern in the moſt ſenſible and obliging Terms, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring her dear <hi>Pariſatis, That rather than ſuch Wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs ſhould go unpuniſht, ſhe her ſelf would be her Champion, and not only all her Intereſt with the King, but her whole power in the World ſhould be arm'd againſt him. Pariſatis</hi> (who indeed expected no leſs from her kind <hi>Statiry,</hi>) fell upon her Knees to thank her for her Royal Goodneſs. When the Queen raiſing her up, adviſed her to have her Woman appear pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickly againſt him, (nor need ſhe fear the Monſieur, for her ſelf would be her Guard) and confront him with it to the open Face of the World; and if he were paſt all ſhame, and the Diſgrace of ſo unprince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Deſign ſo loudly detected would not be puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſufficient, then to leave his farther proſecution to her ſelf. <hi>Alas Madam,</hi> replied <hi>Pariſatis, pardon me when I tell you that ſuch a proceeding againſt him would be the moſt ill managed policy imaginable; for as the Menſieur had harden'd guilt enough to hatch ſuch a piece of Treachery, he has no leſs harden'd Confidence (no doubt) to deny it too: and what would the ſingle Breath of a creature of her low Quality ſignifie in ſo hainous a charge againſt a Prince of the Blood; and how much would the Reputation of the Mounſieur, in the popular Ballance, out-weigh the credit of ſo poor an Accuſer: and ſo the whole Impeachment irſtead of puniſhing the guilty Monſieur, rather retort and wound the innocent</hi> Pariſatis; <hi>when the misjudging World, upon ſuch a Defeat, might be too apt to lay the original Malice of the Accuſation not at the Servant but the Miſtriſes Door? No, Madam, If I would wake ſome able Juſtice in my Cauſe, the only means of gaining that point would be, by having the Monſieur caught at the guilty Hour in my Chamber, with ſome more Authentick Witneſs planted there to confront his intended Wickedneſs; ſome Witneſs (if ſuch a one could be obtain'd) whoſe not only Credit but Power alſo ſhould be able both to publiſh and avenge my Wrongs.</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:31510:29"/> The Queen as if inſpired with a ſuddain Thought from this Hint, of doing ſome extraordinary Act of Friendſhip to ſerve her <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> told her, <hi>That ſince not only the Train was laid againſt the Honour of her dear</hi> Pariſatis, <hi>but the very Scene of his Treachery was moſt audaciouſly laid too under her own Roof</hi> [for the Reader is to underſtand that by the Favour of the Queen, <hi>Pariſatis</hi> lay in an Apartment belonging to the Queens Lodgings, their Beds not many part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Walls between 'em] <hi>ſhe her ſelf would be that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fronting Teſtimony againſt him, for ſhe intended this night to change Beds with her</hi> Pariſatis. <hi>In ſhort ſhe would have Candles lighted up in the Room to receive him; and the Monſieur at the hour admitted.</hi> By this means the unexpected Appearance of the Queen, ſhe was well aſſured, would not only ſufficiently ſtagger her Wicked Brother, and load him with Confuſion; but likewiſe the Reprimand ſhe would entertain him with ſhould prepare him to expect no common Vengeance in her own Royal Vindication of her <hi>Periſatis.</hi> Nor did ſhe doubt to do her this more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant ſervice, from the management of this diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Villany, as to enforce him to make her no leſs a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, for that and all other his loud Abuſes, by no meaner an Atonement, then marrying of her; whilſt the Gratitude of <hi>Pariſatis</hi> threw her immediately at her Feet to embrace her Knees for ſo aſtoniſhing a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
            <p>To put this lively project in Execution, the Night approaches, and the generous Queen is privately ſtoln into her <hi>Pariſatis</hi> Bed; where ruminating with a thouſand various thoughts, and all the preparing Thunder for the approaching <hi>Orleance;</hi> when her long waiting for the expected Traytor had almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luded her into a ſlumber, inſtead of the criminal <hi>Monſieur,</hi> the more guilty <hi>Chevalier,</hi> in only a Night<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gown, bolts in upon her. The Queen had hardly fully open'd her Eyes to ſee the Idol of her Soul ſo near her, when the Ardence of his Burning Lips and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:31510:29"/> twining Arms around her, (a Circle that ſoon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured up thoſe ſtrange bewitching Demons that huſht all other interpoſing Powers,) ſo totally enchanted all the Reaſon and Reſolution about her, that ſhe had not ſcarce a Hand, a Look, a Breath, or a Murmur to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt him. Whilſt the poor betrayed Queen thus loſt, for ever loſt, the uncheckt Riffler plays the lawleſs Rioter, and the yielding Sacrifice is all his own. But here let Modeſty draw the Vail, and lead the bluſhing Reader to the Cardinal, who hugs his darling Niece for this pregnant and proſperous Miſchief; where the poor <hi>Pariſatis</hi> could not forbear ſome very ſharp Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the Undertaking the Cardinals com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand had put her upon; when beſides the betraying of her Royal Friend, a Conſideration of it ſelf alone too poynant, ſhe had ſo poorly debaſed her ſelf to the acting even of the vileſt and moſt deſpicable Office of the moſt Sordid of her Sex. But the Cardinal en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſmooth this little Roughneſs, by guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Meanneſs of the office, with the Glory of the Revenge, and the National Benefit from ſo kind and ſo Meritorious a Treaſon.</p>
            <p>But to raiſe the blooming bluſhing Queen from the Arms of her now too dear Chevalier, no ſooner did ſhe ſet her firſt Eye upon the Cardinal (for the Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſconding <hi>Pariſatis</hi> for ſome few days avoided her ſight) but ſhe whiſpered in his Ear. <hi>Well Cardinal, Cardinal, you have gained your wicked End; but look to it, Church-man, look to it, and ſee there be that Mercy, that forgiving Goodneſs in Heaven for the unhappy</hi> A—a, <hi>that your Religious Sophiſtry has flattered me with: Have a care of my Soul, I charge you, for I have given my ſelf away.</hi> The Cardinal immediately gave her ſo many tender and healing Ghoſtly Comforts, which in truth he applied freſh and warm every day to her, till the Queen at laſt grew almoſt an Enthuſiaſt in Love, ſo artfully the Cardinal diſtilled and infuſed Religion into the Philter, till her Zeal even warm'd with her Kiſſes, and ſhe play'd the very Bigot in Pleaſure. And
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:31510:30"/> for the ſeducing <hi>Pariſatis,</hi> though ſhe gave her at firſt ſome ſmall Rebuke, her Anger was but plumed with Down; ſo much the ſweetneſs of the Treaſon had ato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the Traytor.</p>
            <p>This unreſtrain'd Looſe of Life continuing, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is very quickly bleſt with the reſounding Fame of the Queens being with Child, whilſt ſuch Bonfires and Illuminations are ſet a blazing, that univerſal Joy ecchoes through all <hi>France.</hi> And really even <hi>Lewis</hi> himſelf was the leading Maſter of the Ceremonies, whilſt by his own ſpecial Mandat a Solemn Thanks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving was commanded through the whole Nation. But when the happy day, the crowning Felicity came, that a young <hi>Dauphin</hi> was born, the Celebrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Nativity was a perfect Jubilee; and ſuch ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn and magnificent Proceſſions were made, that he was almoſt careſt with Hoſannahs and Haſlelujahs. Nay, the very Poets of the Age were buſied on that only Theme, and all the Nine Siſters labour'd with no other Birth. Thus after Twenty Three Years worn out Patience was <hi>Lewis</hi> XIV. the Tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated Son of <hi>Lewis</hi> XIII Miracled into the Royal Heir of <hi>France,</hi> and juſtly honour'd with the famous Title of <hi>Dieu-Donne,</hi> Given of God.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is lately Publiſhed the Life and Reign of <hi>Innocent</hi> XI. late Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> whereunto is prefixed his Eſſigies: Written by an Impartial Hand.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:31510:30"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
